- The seven processes.
So, up to this point,
we've talked about PRINCE2
and we've talked about the
principles and the themes,
but now, we're going to
dig into the processes.
This is really where we start applying all
of those principles
and all of those themes
to really make sure our project
is going to go off without any issues.
Now, the seven processes
are going to describe
which role from the
project management team
is responsible for making decisions
when decisions need to be made,
and when should those decisions be made.
So, this could be from the executive,
the senior user, the senior supplier,
the change authority, or the
project manager themself.
Each of those are going to be responsible
for certain decisions
throughout the processes,
and we're going to talk about that
as we dig through these.
Now, when we talk about
the seven processes,
we start with starting up a project.
Then, we move into directing a project,
initiating a project,
managing a stage boundary,
controlling a stage,
managing product delivery,
and finally, wrapping up
and closing a project.
As we move through the cycle,
you'll see that these
are much more sequential,
as opposed to our
principles and our themes,
which could be applied at any time.
Now, when we're dealing with processes,
it's really important
to consider them in time
because these things are going to happen,
some of them together, but
many of them are sequential,
one after the other.
So, here on the screen, you
can see my process timeline.
This is a really handy chart
and one I recommend you
print out and learn.
Now, you can see across the top,
I have Pre-Project, Initiation Stage,
Subsequent Stages, the Final Stage,
and Post-Project.
And you can see that
we start out with this,
providing the project mandate.
Then, it goes into
starting up the project.
Next, we have the initiation stage,
and that's going to be
initiating the project,
managing a stage boundary,
and directing a project.
In the subsequent stages,
we have a lot of those same things,
but we add controlling a stage
and managing product delivery.
And then, we have our final stage,
where we are going to control the stage,
manage project delivery, and
ultimately close the project.
Now, we're going to talk
about each of these blocks
and each of these processes
as we go through these next seven lessons,
so stick with me.
We're going to learn
all about the processes.