- Organization.
The second theme we're going to talk about
here is organization.
Now, when we talk about
organization this is how we're
going to define and set up a
project management team structure.
And we're going to
dictate the accountability
and responsibility for this project.
This is going to implement our
defined roles and responsibility
principle and really help
us get organized as we move
forward with the project.
Because, as I said before,
if you don't clearly identify
people's roles and
responsibilities your project
is likely to fail.
Now when we talk about PRINCE2 we've mentioned over
and over this is a customer
supplier environment.
The customer is the one
who specifies the result
of the project, which is
going to be your end product.
They're going to pay for the
project and they're going to be
the ones realizing the
benefits from the project.
Your suppliers are going
to be the people, the team,
and the organization that
is supplying the product
as requested by the customer.
Now, if the work is conducted
within your own organization
your customer and supplier
can both be inside your
organization but maybe
from different departments.
For example, if you're building
a website you may have the
web development team in IT
building the website to support
the customer who is your
sales and marketing team.
And you can see how this
customer supplier relationship
works inside the company as
well as if you went outside
the company for that web development.
Now when we look at the
project board, we have the
project board that is made up
of three key roles, and these
are your key decision makers.
This is your executive, your senior user,
and your senior supplier.
When we talk about the project
board itself this board is
the one who has the authority
to make the decisions to
approve your plans, approve
your deviations from your plans,
and approve the resources
needed for this project.
The project board should be no more than
five to seven people, because
as they get larger and larger
it gets harder to make decisions.
The executive has the deciding
vote on everything though,
because they're the ones
who have the responsibility
to do this work.
The executive makes the
decisions, but the senior user,
and senior supplier get
to inform and recommend
and provide advice to them.
Remember, the project
board is not a democracy.
It really is more of a
dictatorship, but it's
a benevolent dictatorship,
where the executive relies on
the advice and counsel of
other people on the boards
to make sure the project is successful.
Now, when we look at the
executive this is a role that is
performed by only one person.
You can't have multiple
people being the executive.
The executive is going to
represent the business.
They're going to represent
the customer who is paying
for this project.
So, if we go back to my web
design example, the executive
probably should be somebody
coming from sales and marketing.
Because they are going to be
the end user of that product,
and they're going to be the
ones who are paying for it.
They are responsible ultimately
for the project's success
or failure, and that's why
they get to make the decisions,
based on the advice of the senior user,
and the senior supplier.
Now the senior user is
a role that specifies
and realizes the benefits.
What do we want out of this project?
So, again going back to our
web design example, this is
probably somebody from sales
and marketing, since they are
the ones who are going to be
using and providing service
to that website at the end.
They're responsible for ensuring
the project actually meets
the requirements and get
products out that are usable
and we can realize benefit from.
Now, when we look at our
senior supplier, they're
accountable for bringing
all the required skills
and resources to this project.
And so, they're responsible
for the project's quality.
Going back to my web design
example, the senior supplier
would be somebody from the
web development or IT team,
because they're the ones who
are providing the service
to our customer sales and marketing.
Kind of see all this
starts working together.
That's the idea here, but
having clear lines of roles
and responsibility makes
it easy to know who is
in charge of what thing,
and when something goes wrong
who are we going to blame?
So, there is this other role
out there called project
assurance, now the project
board is going to be telling
the project manager what to do,
based on approving their
plans the project manager's
going to go out and do that work.
Well project assurance is
there to make sure the project
manager does their job properly.
This role is used to assure
the project board, which is
the executive, the senior
user, and the senior supplier,
that the project is
being conducted properly.
This role cannot be held by
the project manager themselves
because that would be like
checking your own homework,
right, you need somebody else to check it.
And so, it can be held by a
project management board member,
like the senior user, the senior
supplier or the executive,
or it can be delegated down
to a third party person
within the organization.
This person is going to give
advice to the project manager
when needed and they're
going to review the documents
before they make their way
up to the project board.
They are that quality assurance
check inside of our project.
Now, the project manager, this
is the person doing the work.
This is the person responsible
for the day to day project
management activities, and
reporting progress back to
the project board.
So, they're going to create
the highlight report,
which we've talked about
before, and the exception report
when we go outside of tolerances.
Using these two reports, they're
going to feed information
up to the project board, so
they can decide whether or not
the project should continue
forward, or should be canceled,
but again, before those reports
go up, they're going to go
through project assurance to
make sure the project manager
isn't hiding anything.
That's the whole idea here, is
making sure we have a system
of checks and balances so the
project goes successfully,
and no single person becomes that single
point of failure.
The team manager works for
the project manager, and there
may be multiple team managers.
These are the people who
manage teams of specialists,
with the required skills
to enable the design,
and production of a product
specified by the customer.
So, if we go back to my web
design example, there may be
a team who's working on
graphics, and another team who's
working on the code.
And another team that's working on the
servers and the infrastructure.
And all three of those will report up to
the project manager.
Now, these teams are responsible
for delivering products
on time and within tolerances,
based on the team plans
that they've been given
from the project manager.
They're going to be reporting
periodically back up to the
project manager who then
takes that information and
consolidates it in their reports.
Whether that's the highlight
report or the exception report
back up to the project board.
The next role we have is something called
the change authority.
Now the change authority
is responsible for making
decisions about requests
for change, rfc's and
off specification requests.
We're going to cover this more
in the change theme so for now
just think about the change
authority as the person who
can approve changes because
that's what they do.
Because any time you have a
change, that's usually going to
cost more money or it's
going to save some money.
And it's going to change the
requirements for the end product.
For example, if you were
building a house and you had
designed it as a three bedroom
two bath house, and now
the person who's house it is
comes and says, you know what
I changed my mind, now
I want three bedrooms
and three bathrooms.
Well, now that they want that
change you're going to have to
go through and make a bunch of
other changes to the project
to add that third bathroom.
Because that third bathroom
didn't exist before.
And if you put it in
you're going to lose space
from something else.
Maybe you're not going
to have a closet anymore.
But now you're going to need
additional plumbing, and that can
cost more or less money
depending on the change.
Somebody has to be the
approval authority for that
change in the project, and that's what the
change authority does.
Now, there's another role
that works underneath the
project manager that's an optional role,
and it's called project support.
This is someone who's going
to assist the project manager
and the team managers with
the daily administration,
report generation, progress monitoring,
and other necessary tasks.
If it's a small project you
may not have project support.
You as the project manager may be
the project support yourself.
If you're in a large project
though, you're probably going to
have somebody to help you,
because if you're in a large
project a single project
manager can't handle everything
by themselves, especially if
they're getting bogged down
in all those change requests,
all those exceptions, all
those highlight reports and
everything else they need to do.
And that's why they'll have
this team of project support
to help them out.
Now, I know we've covered
a lot of different
roles out there.
We talked about the executive,
and the senior user,
and the senior supplier,
and the project manager,
and the team manager,
and the project support,
and the change authority.
All of these roles can have
more than one person assigned
to them except the executive.
As you remember, the executive
is the sole person who's
overall responsible for the project.
But even the project manager
if you have a really large
project you may have a project
management team of three
or four or five people acting
as the project manager.
Some of these roles can
actually be combined as well.
So, if you're in a small
project you can have
one person who's doing multiple roles.
As I mentioned, your
project manager may also be
your project support, two
different roles being met
by one person.
Now, just like we had the
executive was a role that only
one person can hold, project
assurance is a role that
cannot be combined with other things.
Your project assurance
cannot be combined with your
project manager, your team manager,
or your project support roles.
Because again, the project
assurance is overseeing those
three roles to make sure they're
doing their jobs properly.
If you want to combine project
assurance with something else,
it has to be combined
with either the executive,
the senior user, or the senior
supply role, somebody from
that project board because they
oversee those positions anyway.
Now, when we start talking
about all of this, there are all
of these different roles
and they all have an
interest in this project.
Anyone with an interest
in the project is known
as a stakeholder.
These are people who care
about the project's outcome.
They care about this thing
coming to life, this product.
And all these roles are going to
be considered as stakeholders.
But they're not the only ones,
in fact you have people who
are the end users of your product.
They are stakeholders as well.
You also have other departments
within your organization,
they are going to be stakeholders.
There is really no limit to
who could be a stakeholder
when it comes down to
anyone with an interest
in the project.
The determination of the
project board will be determining
who is a valid stakeholder
that they actually
want to hear from.
So, if I'm building a website,
one of my stakeholders
may be my end customer, but
I may not take the time to
talk to my customer and do
that research and communication
about everything that I'm building.
I may only be keeping that
internal within my organization.
So, some stakeholders will be
consulted and others will not.
It's really up to your
project board who they
want to handle that.
Now, just like we talked about
in business case there were
some documents that had to be created.
There are some documents
that need to be created here
in the organizational theme.
One of those is called the
communication management approach.
This answers the question of
how you're going to communicate
with those stakeholders, the ones that you
wish to communicate with.
You're going to have to identify
their information needs.
The method that's going to
be used for communication
is it a meeting, is it a
report, is it an email.
You also have to identify the
frequency of that communication.
Is it going to be daily
or weekly or monthly?
These are all things you have
to determine, and once you do
you write them down
inside your communication
management approach.
For example, your project
board might require a monthly
highlight report from the
project manger, or they may
require a weekly one.
It really depends on how
they want to approach this.
And this communication management
approach will be drafted
up by your project manager and submitted
to the board for approval.
When you look at this
organizational theme we talked about
a lot of roles and responsibilities,
and I want you to see
all on a nice clear chart, which is what
I have here on the screen.
Remember, the project is going
to be approved ultimately by
corporate or program management
at the top of the pyramid.
They are going to establish an executive
inside the project board.
That project board will
have a senior user,
or more than one.
It'll have an executive only
one, and it'll have a senior
supplier or more than one.
Underneath the project board
the change authority and the
project manager work directly
for the project board.
Underneath the project manager
you have the team managers.
And underneath them you
have the team members.
The project manager may have
project support, which is why
there's a dash line there,
and you have project assurance
it is also a dash line that
would either be overseeing
the project management or
that role would be delegated
upward to a senior supplier or senior user
to take on that responsibility.
So, hopefully this helps bring
all of this together in one
nice clean chart for you to see how all
of this coordinates together.
Now, just like we did with
the business case theme,
here in the organizational
theme there are a couple of
key things you have to
do to be able to meet the
requirements for it.
The minimum requirements are to define
the organizational structure.
Creating a chart that looks something
like the one I just showed you.
You're going to create it for
your organization and assign
those people into those roles.
You're going to define those
roles and responsibilities,
including role descriptions.
Now, what is a role description?
A role description is a short
document, usually no more
than a page or two that says
what that role or that position
is responsible for doing.
In that way when you assign
somebody as the senior user
you give them this document
and say here's what's
expected of you.
And that way they know what
they're going to be expected to do,
and they can say yes
or no to that position.
And the third thing you need
to do is produce two documents,
the first is a project initiation
document, and the second
is a communication management approach.
We'll talk more about the
project initiation document
when we get into processes,
and we talk about
initiating a project, because
it's a much more in depth
document and it's required before you can
start your project up.