- Exam Fundamentals.
So what are you really
here in this class for?
Well, you're probably here
because you're going to take
the PRINCE2 foundation exam.
And so you want to
learn all about PRINCE2,
so you can pass that exam.
But before we do that, let's
talk about the exam itself,
just for a couple of minutes.
The exam is the first level
of certification in PRINCE2.
There's actually two other
levels that you could go for.
And the PRINCE2 foundation is going to
introduce the method of PRINCE2.
It really tests, do you understand PRINCE2
and can you work in a project team
that uses the PRINCE2 environment.
You have to pass this
foundation level exam
before you can take one of the other two,
if you desire to continue.
And those are the practitioner and
the agile practitioner certifications.
The PRINCE2 foundation
exam is a 60 question exam
that you have to take in under 60 minutes.
The good news is, it's
a multiple choice exam.
So you just have to be able
to recognize the right answer.
You don't have to
regurgitate it in an essay
or a short answer format.
Now the exam itself only requires
55 percent correct to pass.
That's 33 correct answers
out of 60 possible questions.
The exam is closed book,
so you can't take any notes
into your testing environment,
and you can't use any study guides.
It all has to be
recognized from your brain.
And finally, an important
thing, is that this exam
and this course is based off
of the January 2018 update,
which is that PRINCE 2017 objectives
we talked about in the last lesson.
So are you ready to go sit for the exam?
Well probably not yet, 'cause you're
just starting this course.
But how do you know when you are ready?
Well you should take practice exams.
And at the end of this
course I've provided you with
two full length practice exams to try.
If you're scoring at
least 70 percent or higher
on those practice exams,
you're ready to take
the real certification.
Now, why do I say 70
percent if the passing score
is only 55 percent on test day?
Well, because a lot of things
are factors on test day.
You may be nervous.
You may not have gotten
a good night sleep.
All these different things
can affect your test score.
And I've seen students who have a variable
of about 10 percent in their test score.
So if you're scoring 70% on my exam,
you may score 80 percent on test day,
or you may score 60 percent.
Either way though, you'd pass.
And that's why we set
the bar at 70 percent.
Because I want to make
sure you only have to take
the PRINCE2 exam once, because
it does cost a lot of money
to sit for that exam.
So what do you do if you're not scoring
70 percent or higher?
Well you want to go back and
study the areas that you're
missing, but you want
to continue to take new
and varied practice exams.
So if you need more
practice, take additional
practice exams.
You can find them on my website,
you can find them on Udemy,
you can find them
elsewhere on the internet,
but take a couple of practice exams
until you're scoring at least 70 percent.
Because you really only want
to attempt the certification
exam once, and you want to
pass it on your first attempt.
This course is going to
teach you everything you need
to be able to pass it
on your first attempt.
But you've got to get
comfortable with taking those
practice exams because that's
what you're going to be doing
on test day.
Now, when you pass the exam,
and notice I said when,
not if, when you pass it
I want to hear about it.
So post in the Q and A section,
post in our Facebook group
and let me know when you are
PRINCE2 foundation certified.
Now once you are certified,
where do you go from there?
Well for many, this is going
to be the only certification
project management you want to get.
But for others, you may
want to move up the chain,
and from the PRINCE2
foundation there are two places
you can go, the practitioner
and the agile practitioner.
The PRINCE2 practitioner
is designed for people
who are going to manage the projects.
Remember, we said the foundation level
was for people who are
working inside the projects
as part of the team.
But practitioner is the guy who's
going to be leading the team.
It focuses on the day-to-day
workings of PRINCE2
and how to apply and tailor the method
to different project
environments you may come across.
Like I said, PRINCE2 is very flexible.
But if you're dealing with a large project
that's like building a house,
or a small project like
making a catering event, either
way PRINCE2 can fit for it
but you have to understand
how to apply it.
And that's what the practitioner
exam really focuses on.
Now on the bottom of the
screen here you can see
the agile practitioner.
This is that second
exam, and this focus is
for people who are
using PRINCE2 in a Scrum
or Kanban agile environment.
And this is going to be focused
on working with projects,
products, and program delivery in a very
time compressed format.
So whichever one your organization uses,
that's the one you should be going for,
whether its the practitioner
or the agile practitioner.