- Initiating a project.
Now that we have looked
at starting up a project,
and directing a project,
that brings us to initiating the project.
This is where we're going to establish
the sound foundations for this project
and enable the organization to understand
the work that's going to need to be done
to deliver an actual
product at the end of it,
before we start agreeing to spend
a significant amount of
time, money, and resources.
Let's look at this on
the process timeline.
You can see here,
we started in the pre-project phase.
Somebody had a good idea and a
project mandate was provided.
We then went through and started up
a project to support this great idea
that we think had a valid business case.
The project board is then
working to direct the project.
You can see how it goes from
starting up a project up,
back to that high level
and down into the directing a project.
Directing a project is going to tell
the initiation of a project
that they need to go forth
and create the process
initiation document,
or the PID, which we've
mentioned several times before.
But we're going to talk about it much more
in depth in this lesson.
Then, once we get that valid PID,
and we know what those benefits are,
and the time and the scope,
it's going to go back up
to directing a project
for their approval and this
project will become initiated.
Let's go ahead and look at
what the objectives are.
Our objectives of initiating a project
are to identify the reasons,
the time scale, the cost,
the scope, the major products,
the expected benefits,
and any risk we can think of
associated with this project.
This project, we also need to identify
the quality requirements and the standards
that are going to be used.
We need to identify what
a baseline product will be
and how it's going to be controlled
through change management.
And then we also need to
identify our communications plan
and what are the communication
needs of our stakeholders
and how we're going to meet those.
A lot of those things
we've talked about already
are now coming together
inside initiating a project.
Now, when we look at all of that,
the main product we're going to have
is what's called the project
initiation document, the PID.
And it has to contain the project plan.
What stages will there be and
how many stages will there be?
It needs to have a detailed business case.
We're going to take the outline
and make it fully formed at this point.
We're going to have a
communication management approach.
Who are we going to talk to,
at what frequency and with what method?
We're going to have a
risk management approach
so that we can codify that
risk theme into this process.
We're going to have a
quality management approach
so again, we're going to
take the quality theme
and make it get some legs
and start putting it into this project.
We're going to look at change theme
and use the change control approach,
and start moving that through the process.
We're going to also have project controls,
so we know what are the time
and tolerance controls we're going to use.
We're going to have any
PRINCE2 tailoring we do,
has to be identified
here in our PID as well.
Like we talked about all
the way back in principles.
So, you can see how those principles
and themes start coming together now,
inside this project initiation document,
which happens inside the
initiating a project process.
Now, the outputs from initiating a project
are obviously going to be the PID,
the project initiation document.
But the other output we need
is a benefits management approach.
If you remember back,
who was in charge of the
benefits management approach?
The benefits management approach
was the responsibility of the senior user.
They're going to describe how the benefits
are going to be measured,
how often and by whom.
They're also going to update it at the end
of the project and turn this over,
because it becomes an active document
that's going to be used during
the products operational lifetime.
It's also going to be turned
over to the corporate office,
the program management office,
or the customer at the project closure,
so they know what those things are.
What does this really look
like in the real world?
Let's say I was building a network.
The senior user might have told me
that one of the things we were
going to do was measure uptime.
That's what's going to be measured.
We're going to measure it every week
and take an average and
it's going to be measured
by the service operations team.
That is what the benefit is,
how much uptime, how often, and by whom.
Now, when we build,
we're building it to meet
those project, those benefit.
Now, when I build this network,
I'm going to build it to meet
the benefits management approach.
I want to make sure I meet
the metrics I was told.
Say, 99% uptime.
But, once I build this network
and turn it over to the customer,
it's not my problem anymore,
the project is over, right?
So, I'm going to turn
that approach over to them
so they know how they can measure it
and make sure they're maintaining
the uptime that they need
for that product to be successful.