- Plans.
So the plans theme is going to help us
to facilitate communication
and control by defining the means
of delivering the products.
This is where we start building our plans
that we can work towards
to build our products.
This is going to define the how,
when, how much, by whom,
and where the project will deliver
the final products and outcomes.
There are three levels of plans
that we've mentioned before.
The project plan, the stage
plan, and the team plan.
Now, the project plan is
used by the project board.
This is going to contain
the project level costs,
the timescales, and the control points.
It's going to tell us how
many stages there are,
and when those stages happen.
It's going to be updated at the end
of each stage to reflect
the actual progress
and revise forecast so we know going
forward what we are budgeting for.
Underneath those, we're
going to have the stage plan,
and the stage plan is going
to have one per project stage.
It's used for the day-to-day management
of the project by our project manager.
And then we have our team plan,
and this is going to be
used by our team managers.
This is also known as work packages.
These cover the work to be done by a team.
And there can be multiple work packages
or multiple team packages in
existence at any one time.
So if I'm using the example
of building a house,
maybe we are in the stage
where we're going to build a bathroom.
In that stage, I'm going to
have a plumber's work package,
I'm going to have an
electrician's work package,
somebody to tile the floors,
and somebody to install the fixtures,
so maybe three, four, five
different work packages.
But they're still only one stage
and that stage is one piece
of the larger project plan
that is used to build the whole house.
So you can see these things
nest inside of each other.
Now, when I look at an exception plan,
this is when something goes wrong
and I have to deviate
from the project plan,
the stage plan, or the team plan.
A new plan will be created
to replace one of those,
either the stage plan
or the project plan to overcome an issue.
This is not an updated
version of an existing plan,
but it's instead a change and a new way
of approaching things.
Corporate or program
management are the ones
to approve a change to the project plan,
and the project board will
change the stage plan.
So remember, the stage plan is
used by the project manager.
If there is an exception,
his bosses, the project board,
need to make that change.
Just like the project plan
is owned by the project
board and the executive.
If there needs to be a change to it,
they have to go to their boss,
which is corporate or program management.
And so it keeps going up the
ladder to get that change made.
Now, when we look at budget planning,
we have to plan and consider
for many different things.
The first is the product
and management funding.
Because there's costs associated
with building this final product
and there's overhead to pay
the project manager, the project board,
and all the people doing that.
This is the activities
to create the specialized products
and the management of those products.
We also need a change budget,
and that's because nothing
is going to go perfectly the way you plan.
There's always going to
be some sort of change
that's requested by your customer.
Change budget is used
for authorized changes
to the baseline products.
So when they've gotten version one out,
and now we are trying to get version 1.1,
because somebody decided
to change the font on our slide deck,
or they wanted to change the
graphics used on the website.
Whatever those things are,
we have to pay for that,
and the change budget
pays for those changes.
This goes through the
change management process,
through an RFC or request for change,
and the change authority
has this change budget
that they can authorize
and pay for changes with.
There's also a risk budget,
because there is risk
inherent in everything we do.
And so activities that need
to respond to risk are going to be covered
from the risk budget.
Maybe we are building a house
and it rained so much
that we can't pour the foundation
without draining the lot
and we need to rent some
pumps to get the water out.
Well, those pumps could be
paid for using the risk budget.
It was something that wasn't planned for,
it wasn't something that was expected,
and so the risk budget
can pick up the slack.
And finally, we have cost tolerance.
Cost tolerance is any cost overruns
that happen within a certain tolerance.
We talked about tolerances
back in the last section
of this course, and we talked about
that we may have a plus
10% tolerance on something.
Well, if it's $100,000 project,
we would then have a $10,000,
so if it's $100,000 project,
we would have 10,000 or 10%
set aside for cost overruns
that are within tolerance.
And if it's within the tolerance,
you don't have to go up to your
boss to ask for more money,
because you have that money available.
Now, when we talk about
product-based planning,
we're going to write a
project product description,
and that's going to define
what the project must deliver.
So what is that end product?
Is it the house?
Is it a car?
Is it a website?
Is it a network?
Whatever that thing is,
we have to write up a description of it,
and it's not just going to
say that this is a red car,
but we're going to talk about the fact
that it's a red four-door sedan
that can go zero to 60 in five seconds.
And do x, y, z, and et cetera.
That's your product description.
You're also going to have
to create a product breakdown structure.
So using our car example,
there are other products
that have to built to go into the car.
I need airbags, I need seats.
I need upholstery.
I need gauges.
I need wiring.
And we're going to break those down
into individual smaller products
that we can then put into
the larger, car product.
We also need to write product descriptions
and these are written requirements
for every major product.
So if I need an airbag,
I better write the
description of that airbag.
How fast will it deploy?
How much pressure can it take?
All of those types of facts and figures.
And finally, we need to
create a product flow diagram.
This is what you've probably
seen of as a Gantt chart.
If you see the icon above my head,
that's really a simple version
of a product flow diagram.
You can see there's
four different products,
and I'm on schedule on the top two
and I'm not on the bottom two.
And where we are and what needs to be done
in which sequence,
and usually you'll see for instance
that you have to do item one
before you can do item two.
So if I go to my house example,
I have to pour the foundation
before I can put up the walls.
I need to put in the electrical
and the plumbing before
I put in the drywall.
I need the drywall to be
in before I can paint it.
And so as a product manager,
I need to be able to time and sequence all
of these things to get the most done
in the least amount of time.
I can have the electricians
and the plumbers working at the same time,
but I can't have the
drywallers in there too,
because they'll be covering up areas
that those two other teams need.
That's the idea here when
you start creating your
product flow diagram.
It doesn't necessarily
need dates at this point,
but it does need to know
big muscle movement a needs
to come before muscle movement b.
Then we start looking at
planning for our stages.
We start bundling things together.
We're going to have to determine
how long each stage is going to be.
And we talk about stages,
we're going to talk about the fact
that you have to have a minimum
of two stages inside of PRINCE2.
You must have initiating a product stage,
and then you have to have
conducting the stage itself.
And so that'll be two different stages.
But you can have many many
more stages than that.
And so you're going to have
to determine how many stages there will be
for your particular project.
For small projects, you may
only have the minimum of two.
If you're doing something large,
it may be five, 10, or 15 stages.
It really depends on how
comfortable the project board
is with that project manager,
and how much room between
go/no go decisions they want.
How far out can you realistically plan?
That's your planning horizon.
The longer you can see out,
the more they're going to
allow you to have less stages.
How many delivery steps will there be?
Are we going to deliver
everything in one big piece,
or we've only got a website
with 10 different features
and we're going to do 10
stages, one for each feature?
Does it align with other program
activities that are going on?
And what level of risks there is.
If it is a more risky project,
you will have more stages.
If it is a less risky project,
you will have less stages.
I'll give you a great example of this.
Recently, I built a house
about two years ago for us to live in.
And when we built this house,
we went with a builder who
builds a lot of houses.
And so there was only three
stages that were done,
and of those three stages,
they came back to us
for go/no go decisions.
Now, we felt very comfortable with that,
because this builder builds
hundreds of houses a year,
and in fact they only
build five floor plans.
And we had one of those five floor plans.
And so they had built this
same house many many times.
So it was a very low
risk environment for us,
and so we only had to have
that go/no go decision three times.
Now, if it was the first time
they've ever built the house,
and it was a custom house,
and there was all these
different changes going on,
we might have had five,
10, or 15 stages where we
can constantly have those
touch points to come
back and check on them.
But because this was
something that was low risk,
we didn't need that many stages.
So when it comes to plans,
PRINCE2 has a couple of
minimum requirements.
The first one is that your plans
have to be created in a way
to enable your business
case to be realized.
We're going to go from idea to product
and to do that, we need a plan.
Second, we are required to produce plans
and you do have to produce
at a minimum your project
plan and your stage plan.
You are not required to use
team plans or work packages
but it is highly recommended.
But the two that are required
is project and stage plans.
Next, you need to produce any
exception plans when required.
So if you go outside of tolerance,
you have to come up with a
way to get yourself back in
or you're going to have
to cancel the project.
We also have to create a
project product description,
our product descriptions
and our product breakdown structures
which give us that timing and
tempo of the different stages.
And finally, you have to go
back to organization again
and define roles and
responsibilities for planning.
Who is going to do this and
what is expected of them?
You'll see these themes come up
over and over and over again,
because even the themes
start building on themselves
and the underlying principles.
(electronic jingle)