- Change, the next thing we're
going to talk about is change,
and change is going to
help us identify, assess,
and control any potential
or approved changes
to our project baseline.
So let's talk about a
baseline a little bit here.
A baseline is used only for products
that have been approved
by those in authority
and is deemed fit for purpose.
It's something that is finished,
it's ready for the next iteration.
The product has been
given a version number.
So if you're dealing
with a software project,
we often call it version
one, version 1.1, version 2.
Version 2, and we have these minor changes
and these major changes.
But any time you change the baseline
going from version 1.0 to the next thing
you have to go through the change theme
and the change management procedures.
Now when we look at a project
there are lots of issues that come up.
In fact, we just talked
about in the risk lecture
all of those risks that
can become realized
and turn into a project issue.
When you have a project issue,
this is an event that has
happened and wasn't planned for.
This is going to require some
sort of management action
to overcome it and move
the project forward.
So this can be a request for change
where we request a change
to the known baseline.
We want to go from version
one to version 1.1.
Or it may be that we need
an off-specification.
This is going to allow
the product requirements
to be changed because we can't
meet the ones as designed.
When I talked before about
the iPhone drop example
if we couldn't drop it from two feet
we may do an off-specification
to allow us to do it
as a drop from one foot.
Then we have problems or concerns.
This is the third type, this is anything
that's outside of an RFC
or an off-specification.
Now if the project issue
will exceed a tolerance
then we have to go through
the exception report,
through the exception process
that the project manager
is responsible for
to inform the project board
because any time you're
going to go outside tolerance
the project board needs to be notified.
Now, the resolution of
these project issues
can happen one of two ways.
There is a formal process
and an informal process.
The formal process is going
to require formal advice
from the project board.
So we put it in our exception report,
the project issue is logged
in the issue register,
and an issue report is
written by the project manager
and submitted to the project board.
They can then go through and decide
are we going to make a change,
are we going to do an off-specification,
or are we going to accept the way it is?
Now informal is the easier
way of doing things,
and this is when the issue is recorded
inside the daily log.
The reason it's easier is
because the project manager
can deal with it at their own level.
This is something they
don't have to bring up
to higher management,
they have enough funds,
they have enough tolerance,
and they can deal with it
and solve the problem themself.
So when it's informal
they're just going to note it
in their notebook, take care
of the issue, and move on.
Now, the change control
approach is going to depend on
the way you decided to set it
up inside of your project.
You're documenting the
way that the project
is going to manage these
issues and changes.
How is that change control going to work?
Who is the change authority?
And what is this process
going to look like?
You're going to have issue
and change control procedures
that provide detailed steps
that you're going to utilize
inside your project.
Now again, PRINCE2 isn't going to dictate
how you have to do this change process.
Instead, it just says you have to have
a change control process,
and that's why you need to
make sure you document it
in your change control approach
in case you ever get audited.
Now, when you look at this issue
and change control procedures,
there are five main steps
but again, you're going to
put the detailed processes
in your project yourself.
You have to capture,
examine, propose, decide,
and implement those changes.
Now when you want to capture the change,
this is where you're
going to record the issue
in either your daily
log if you're doing it
informally as a project manager,
or formally inside the issue register.
Next, you're going to examine that change.
You're going to perform an impact analysis
to determine the impact on your cost,
your time, your quality, your scope,
your benefits, and your risk.
All of these factors are
things you need to consider
because every time you make a change,
it's going to affect this.
It may take more time
or it's going to take more
money to take less time,
or you're going to drop
quality to save some money.
All of these are levers
that have to be moved
in order to make sure your project
gets to its angle on the
right time, the right budget,
the right schedule, to
be deemed successful.
The third step is to propose the change
and this is where you're
going to consider your
alternative options for
responding to the project issue.
There are always more than
one way to solve a problem.
You may have an issue, for example,
in building out a network.
Maybe your routers didn't arrive on time.
Well how are you going
to get back on schedule?
Well, maybe you're going
to spend more money
to expedite the shipping
and get it here faster.
Or maybe you're going to
choose a different vendor.
Or maybe you're going to let
the schedule slip by a week
and you're going to
deliver it a week late.
These are all things you can decide,
but again you have to
propose the way ahead
and what are your courses
of action going to be?
Then next you have to decide.
You're going to determine the best option
for the best overall value for the money.
Now remember, overall value for the money
does not mean cheapest.
You may accept a higher
price for higher quality,
or a higher price for a shorter time.
That is totally acceptable.
It depends on what your
goal of your product
and your project is.
And finally you have to
implement that change.
Now that you've decided what to do,
you need to perform the
recommended course of action
or option to solve your issue.
That gets you past this change issue
to move on to the future.
Now, how do you approve changes?
Well, approval for changes
come from the change authority.
If you remember back in
our organization theme,
I showed you the different diagrams,
the change authority was
shown off to the side.
Now they are the ones
who are going to review
and they're going to approve
your request for change
or your off-specifications.
This can be performed by the
project board by default,
but in larger projects
they're actually going to
delegate that down to somebody else
who is going to work outside
of the project manager
to be that change control process.
Now inside of that person,
that change authority,
that role, there is a change
budget allocated to them.
Just like we had a risk
budget to deal with
those risk mitigations,
we have a change budget
which is a special budget that's set aside
to fund any approved changes.
Now here's where you have to be careful
as a project manager,
because often people try to
steal from the risk budget for a change,
or they try to steal from
the change budget for a risk.
So you want to make
sure you're being honest
when you're choosing which pile of money
that you're going to be using,
depending on if it really is
a risk mitigation, or if it's
a change to the baseline.
Now all of this kind of
comes together inside of
what we call configuration management.
This is where your project
needs to be able to identify
different versions of the
product or products that it has.
This is really easy inside of software
because we're used to
using versioning control.
So we have version one of the software,
version 1.1, version 1.2.
But if you're doing something like
building an apartment building,
people don't often version
control their projects that way
but they should according to PRINCE2.
So once you get to that approved baseline,
that's the way it was built,
that's what we call the as-built,
and anything after that becomes a change
that must go through
configuration management.
If I wanted to move the
wall from here to there
that should go through a change process.
Now the configuration
item record is a document
that is is going to record
the status and version
of a given product.
This can be a paper item
like in a card catalog
or it can be in an electronic database.
Now another part of your
configuration management
is something called the
product status account.
This is a report that
contains the status of
one or more products.
So again, if I'm dealing
with a big piece of software,
I may have five or 10 different functions
that are being built
separately as products.
So each of those, I need
to know the status of it.
Has it been approved or is
it still being worked on?
This is useful for the product manager
to determine if the product was approved
and has a baseline version,
or if it's still undergoing
its quality control or development.
The product status account
is that master list
that lets me know where every
piece of this puzzle is,
and what the status is of it.
Now, when we get to PRINCE2
minimum requirements for change
there are four main ones
we have to consider.
First, we have to define
a change control approach
to describe our issue and
change control procedures used.
Again, PRINCE2 doesn't
care how you do issue
and change control, but the
fact is you have to do it.
Next, we want to maintain
an issue register
for formal changes, or a daily
log for our informal changes
to record and manage all
of our project issues
that happen along the way.
Then we want to define our
roles and responsibilities
for change management because again,
if you don't have well-defined
roles and responsibilities
like who is the change authority?
Who can approve use of the change budget?
Those are things that need to be defined.
If you don't have that,
you're going to falter.
Then we also want to look
at our lessons learned
from past experiences so we can apply them
into our change decisions moving forward.
Because maybe the last time we did this
we decided that our change
was to spend more money
to expedite shipping, but
that made us go over budget
and we weren't successful
in the project anyway,
and we fell behind on time schedule.
So maybe we want to take a
different route this time.
Those are the type of things you can learn
from lessons learned
and previous experience.
(quick electronic music)