- The seven principles.
So welcome to section two,
where we're going to talk about
the seven principles of PRINCE2.
Now, what are the seven principles?
Well, these are the foundational
building blocks of PRINCE2.
PRINCE2 looked back over
30 years, and it looked at
lots and lots of different projects.
And they asked two basic questions.
They said, why did this project succeed?
Or why did this project fail?
And they look at all of those things,
and they came up with these answers.
And these answers are
the seven principles.
They found that if you had
these seven principles,
you were more likely to be
successful in your project.
And if you were missing one
or many of these principles,
your project was more likely to fail.
This is how they proved
what the best practices were
by going back and doing
lots and lots of research.
So what are those seven principles?
Well, they're continued
business justification,
learn from experience,
defined roles and responsibilities,
manage by stages,
manage by exception,
focus on products,
and tailor to the environment.
If your project has these seven principles
as its foundation, it is going
to be more likely to succeed.
And so we're going to
cover each of these in
their own lecture inside of this section.
Let's go ahead and get started with
continued business justification.
(electric static)