- Closing a project.
So our final process is closing a project,
and closing a project is
going to provide us with
a fixed point at which acceptance
of the project's product
has been confirmed.
This is going to recognize
that the objectives set
out in the original
project initiation document
have been achieved and met,
or that the project has
nothing more to contribute
because we're closing it
early because we failed,
or we decided it was no
longer a valid business case.
Now, this is a process, it
is not a separate stage,
as you can see here on
our process timeline.
On our process timeline, you'll
see that closing a project
is a managing level process,
and it's going to occur
in the final stage.
Now, once we get to
this closing a project,
this is going to happen because
we've been told to do it
through the directing a project process,
it will be approved and then
we will close out this project.
Let's talk a little bit more
about closing out a project.
What's involved with that?
Well there's a couple of
things we need to achieve.
We want to ensure that there's
a clear end to the project,
because projects are time constrained,
they shouldn't go on forever and ever,
they should achieve something
as a temporary organization
and then be taken apart.
This is going to ensure that
we can transition the product
of this project to the customer,
make sure they have it,
they've accepted it and
they are now operating it.
We're going to ensure that
project management resources
can be released, so when we
built this whole project,
we had a project board with
an executive and a senior user
and a senior supplier, and
maybe a change authority,
and we had a project manager,
and we had teams that
were working on this.
All those people now that
we're done with the project
can be released back to their own jobs,
and we're also going to
ensure that no more costs
can be incurred by the project.
If you don't close out a
project, there may still be
a line of accounting out there,
and people can be charging things to it,
and so you want to make sure
that is appropriately closed down
as well.
Now in addition to those basic
objectives we talked about,
there's a couple of
follow-on recommendations
that you want to capture as
part of this closing a project.
You want to document any outstanding items
that were never completed,
because maybe you just didn't
get to them, maybe they were
additional things that were
minor things that didn't
need to be completed for this
project to be closed,
or maybe the project was terminated early
and so you have a half finished product.
That needs to be listed so
people can maybe pick it up
later on and run with
it again at a time when
there is a better business case.
Also, if there were any
changes that were asked for
that weren't implemented,
you need to make sure
those are passed on to the
operational customer as well,
and any risks that may
still affect operations,
like we talked about networks,
there's always going to be
some vulnerabilities out there,
there's always going to
be down time concerns,
those type of risks should
be passed on to operations
as well so they can follow up on them.
All of these things will be
part of your end project report
that says what the end
status of this project was.
Now, we are going to create,
as a project manager,
a draft project closure notice.
This is one of our final things that we do
as we prepare it and send
it up to the project board
for their approval.
This happens and then the
directing a project process
will either approve it or deny it.
If they approve our
project closure notice,
that means we can then start
this closing a project process
and close out the project properly.
When the project closure is authorized,
all management projects
should be securely archived
and available for any future audits
because remember, as part of prints two,
somebody can come in
and audit our work later
for quality assurance.
We need to make sure we
don't delete anything,
we want to make sure it's all
properly archived and saved.
So, what is the end state
when we finish the closure
of the project?
Well, the products are
transferred over to the customer
and they're using them
and getting the benefits they thought.
The project management team
is going to return to their
normal roles, or if they're
just a dedicated project
management team, they're going
to start another project.
The benefits of this
project have been realized
by the customer.
We were told to build a
network so that another hundred
employees could be in the building.
Well, we did it, those
hundred employees are there,
they're on the network and
they're working properly.
Great, project can be closed.
And we want to document
any lessons learned again,
because we may use these
in future projects,
so let's take the network example.
If I built a new network
for an office building
that was going to support a hundred users,
do you think I may ever do that again?
Well, certainly, when we
grow for another hundred,
we're going to have to do
the same type of thing again,
so the lessons I learned from this project
will be useful to whoever's
going to be running that project,
so we want to make sure
they're properly captured.