- Managing product delivery.
This process is focused
on controlling the link
between the project manager
and the team manager
or team managers
by agreeing to the
requirements for acceptance,
execution, and delivery
of certain products.
The role of a team manager is
to coordinate an area of work
that will deliver one or more
of the project's products.
So if we go back to my house example,
I might have the plumbing.
That's one team manager.
I have electrical, that's another.
I have the air conditioning,
that's another.
And each of these people are responsible
for certain products being delivered
in the final build of this home.
Now, when we look at this
on the process timeline,
you will see it falls right underneath
the controlling a stage
and that's because a project
manager is responsible
for controlling the stage,
breaking up the work into work packages,
and pushing that down to the team managers
at managing product delivery.
And so when we look at this,
we have a couple of key objectives.
We have to ensure work on products is
allocated to the teams.
Because if the project manager
doesn't approve any work,
nothing's going to get done.
And the project manager is responsible
for authorizing that work
through the form of work
packages or team plans.
They're also going to ensure
the team managers and suppliers
are clear as to what is expected of them
in terms of the cost,
the schedule, the time,
and the effort for a given product.
Going back to our house example,
how quickly do you need that plumbing run?
Well, I expect a three-bedroom,
two-bath house to be run
in two days,
and it's going to cost a thousand dollars,
or whatever that time
and scope is in cost,
you need to agree to that.
You also need to ensure that
your products are delivered
within tolerance.
So if you have a tolerance of two days,
plus or minus one day, they
can deliver it anywhere
between one day and three days, right?
Because that's within your tolerances.
Again, you're going to want
to keep tighter tolerances
on your teams, than you,
as a project manager,
have been given, so you have some room
to deal with the issues
if they exceed them.
And then you want to ensure
accurate progress information
is being provided to the project manager
at agreed upon frequencies
from those team managers.
And we'll talk about how they do that
with the checkpoint reports.
Now, what do I do if my
supplier doesn't use PRINCE2?
Because, in all honesty, most
suppliers don't use PRINCE2.
PRINCE2 is used by project
management professionals.
It's not used by suppliers
most of the time.
Managing product delivery
acts as this interface
between PRINCE2 and the supplier.
Because your supplier doesn't
necessarily need to operate
inside of PRINCE2, instead,
they need to be able to operate
within the bounds of the
work package you give them,
and those work packages are
going to serve as this interface.
To convert things from the project plan
down to the stage plan,
into this little piece
called a work package
that is authorized by the project manager
and fits nicely into this
PRINCE2 architecture.
Now, when we look at a work package,
this is going to provide your team manager
the tolerance they need
that is required for
their product delivery.
This is set by your project manager
when you're dealing with the work package
or team plan level.
Team managers may be
required to make a team plan,
which is authorized by the project manager
or the senior supplier.
Senior suppliers will handle this
for any outside vendors and contracts.
So if I was going to
be buying a whole bunch
of computers to get installed,
that would be handled
by the senior supplier.
If I was going to run a
bunch of network cable
and we already owned it all,
I just had to do it with my IT staff,
that would be something that
would be handled internally
by me as the team manager
or by the project manager,
depending on how your
organization is set up.
Now, when we deal with checkpoint reports,
this is the method that
the team manager uses
to provide accurate updates
and progress reports
up to the project manager.
They'll usually talk about their schedule
and their cost at this point.
This is similar to a highlight report,
but at this lower level
that manages the team plan
or the work package.
Team managers should raise a project issue
to the project manager any time
that a work package or team plan tolerance
may be forecasted to be exceeded.
So if you think you're going
to go outside the bounds
of what the project manager has given you,
you better tell them.
Now, a team manager does not have to write
an exception report.
That's not their role.
They're going to tell the project manager,
and the project manager,
if it's going to go outside
their bounds, will write
the exception report up
to the project board.
(electric blips)