- Welcome to the course.
What is this course all about?
Well, this course is all about
the PRINCE2 Foundation certification.
This course is not going to give you
an in-depth guide to PRINCE2,
but instead we're going to review
all of the main concepts
so you can take and pass
the exam with confidence.
This course is going to cover
the frequently asked concepts
and it's going to help you
focus your study efforts
to the things you need to know
to be able to pass the
Foundation level exam.
Now, who am I?
My name is Jason Dion, I'm a
professor and an instructor.
I've been working in
the cybersecurity field
for about two decades and I
have led and been a part of
many many projects through that time.
I've dealt with projects in
the Information Technology
space as well as in the
Cybersecurity space.
I've dealt with small projects
of just a couple of thousand dollars,
all the way up to large projects
costing several million dollars.
As we go through this course,
I'm going to bring out lots of examples
to help you understand
the PRINCE2 methodology
and how that fits inside
a project management.
Before we get started, I
have a couple of pieces
of important information
I want to share with you.
First, this course is closed captioned,
so if you need to follow along
with the English captions,
you can click on the CC
button on your video player
and you'll be able to
follow along that way.
Second, sometimes I get
excited about this stuff
and I start speaking too fast,
or for some students, they
think I speak too slow.
In either case, the player does allow you
to speed me up or slow me down
by clicking on the 1X button.
Go ahead and click on that button
and you can increase the
speed by going to 1.5 or two,
or you can decrease the speed
by going down to 0.5 or 0.75.
Also, every slide you see in this course
you can download as a PDF file.
Attached to this lecture
you're going to find
a downloadable resource
that has all of the slides
in one convenient download,
so you can print it off
or put it on your Ipad
or your tablet and take it
with you for offline studying.
And finally, if you have a question,
please feel free to post
it in the Q & A section,
or you can join our Facebook group
at facebook.com/groups/diontraining
and interact with me
and your fellow students
as you're studying for this
or other certifications.
And one final disclaimer
before we get started.
I want to remind you that PRINCE2, ITIL,
ITIL v3, ITIL Foundations,
and the Information Technology
Infrastructure Library
are all registered trademarks of AXELOS
in the United Kingdom and other
countries around the world.
I don't own those terms, I'm
just teaching you the concepts
so that you can pass the
PRINCE2 Foundation exam,
so let's get started.