- Manage By Stage.
The next principle we have
is called Manage By Stage.
What this asks the question of,
is how far out can I realistically plan?
What do I mean by that?
When I look at a really
big, large project,
I'm going to have some high-level plan
that covers the whole project.
On the screen you'll see a
map from Baltimore, Maryland
all the way down to
Disneyland in California.
This is a pretty big road trip
if you wanted to drive it.
It's three or four thousand
miles, essentially.
That's going to take us
five, six, or seven days
and I'm not going to be able to
know what the traffic is like
if I look today along that entire route
because it's going to
change on a daily basis.
Instead, I should have a detailed plan
that is added stage by stage.
In my road trip example, maybe
I go and plan a day at a time
and I can look at Google
Maps in the morning
and see what the traffic
patterns are like that day.
When I get to day two,
I might start driving
and be leaving Columbus, Ohio.
I can zoom in and see
what the traffic's like
between Columbus, Ohio
and Springfield, Illinois,
just for an example.
That's a detailed stage plan and
I might be able to figure out, okay,
I'm going to stop for gas here,
I'm going to get lunch here,
and make it much, much more detailed
than if I tried to plan
the entire 3500 mile trip
all at once before I even got in the car.
The same thing holds true
inside of our projects.
We want to manage by stages
because it's more
accurate to plan that way.
We can agree on the detail
for each stage at each stage break.
How much is it going to
cost for the next stage?
How long is it going to
take for the next stage?
Maybe I'm going to say, you
know what, the next two days,
we're going to be driving through
some really expensive places
and it's going to cost
me $300 a day for food.
But then I'm going to go
to some inexpensive places,
it only costs me $100 a day for food.
And so we can plan that, stage by stage,
just like we can inside of our projects.
When we look at this,
you have to ask yourself,
how many stages do you need?
In PRINCE2, you need to have
a minimum of two stages.
You must have an initiation stage,
which is used to plan the overall project,
that large, not detailed map.
And then you need to
have a delivery stage,
or multiple delivery stages,
that are used to deliver
the specialized projects
and those are those detailed stage plans.
In my example of the road trip,
I would have the
initiation stage that plans
the overall route, from
Baltimore to California.
And then I would have delivery
stages of one day each,
so six stages, that
would plan out the detail
of where we're stopping,
what hotel we're staying at,
what food we're going to
get, et cetera, et cetera.
You get the idea.
And before we can leave that stage,
ie, go to sleep up for the night
and pick up the next stage,
we have to have the next
stage planned and ready to go.
The same thing applies
inside of our projects.
This all comes down to the concept
of what's called a planning horizon.
Your plan can only be made to a manageable
level of detail based on the timeline.
If I'm planning out something
that's going to take a week to build,
I can probably do that in two stages,
an initiation stage and a
building or delivery stage.
But if I want to do something
that's going to take nine months,
that may need to have two
or three or four stages.
For example, I built my
house that I'm sitting in.
Well, I didn't build it,
the contractors built.
But when they built out the plan,
we came up with a nine month plan
of what would happen for
us to build this house.
And then, there were
breakpoints along the way
where they stopped and said,
have we met everything
in this particular stage?
Okay, we're going to close that stage
and move to the next stage.
PRINCE2 recommends three levels of plans.
They have a project plan, a stage plan,
and an optional team plan.
Project plans are not very detailed.
They're very big and very broad.
They're going to give things
like time and overall cost
and that's going to be
developed by the project board.
The stage plan is built
by the project manager
and they're going to be more detailed.
And then the team plan is going
to be very, very detailed.
If I look at the example of my house,
one of the teams was the plumbers.
They only had a plan that covered
putting in the plumbing in the house.
But the project manager had a stage plan
that included putting in the plumbing,
the heating and cooling,
putting in the wiring for the
electrical, and the drywall.
All of that was in one stage.
And then the project plan
itself was the overarching plan
that the project board, the
executive, I, had, which was,
I want a finished house
to go from the ground
all the way through to a
house that I could live in.
You can see how this breaks down
from the bigger to the
smaller to the very small.
Each one has more detail than the last.
The initiation stage is going to ensure
all your costs and your
timescales are considered
before you even start the project.
These aren't going to be exact.
It's not going to say, that this
is going to cost me $1,997.23.
It will say, this project will cost me
about two to three thousand dollars,
something generic like that.
You're going to create,
in the initiation stage,
a thing called the Project
Initiation Documentation, or PID.
This is produced inside
the initiation stage.
The project board uses
the PID to determine
the project's viability to
continue to the next stage.
It gives them, what are the
things we must accomplish
before we go to the next stage?
It's going to have that
for all of the stages
for the entire project plan in this PID.
It's going to be that
overview and that outline.
Moving from the initiation stage,
we go into those delivery stages.
Before we move from one stage to the next,
we always have a go/no go decision.
This is where we ask,
should we move forward with the project?
This is going to minimize our risk
by providing cancellation points.
Let's use the example of the road trip.
Let's say we got on the
road and we planned six days
to drive from Baltimore,
Maryland to California.
We go with the first day,
and we get to the hotel,
and we thought it was going
to take us eight hours,
but it really took us 10
hours because of traffic.
Then we assess.
Will we still be able to make
it to California on time?
Yes or no?
Do we even still want to go to California?
And then we'll keep going.
We finish that stage, we
go into the second stage.
We go to day two and we
drive through day two
and it took us 18 hours cause
there was really bad traffic.
Now we're in Columbus,
Ohio, and we're looking out,
we're going, man, for
us to get to California,
it may not be worth it any more.
Let's turn around and go home.
And that's our no go decision.
We don't want to go to the next stage.
We just decide to back
out or cancel the project.
That's the same thing that
happens with our projects.
Every time we hit the end of a stage,
the project manager is going
to update the project plan
with what the forecast was
and what the actual was.
Maybe we thought it was going to cost
$10,000 to do this project
and we start looking
at the end of the stage and
we already spent $12,000.
That would be a bad thing, right.
We already blew the entire budget.
The managers might say, you know what,
we're done, this project's over.
These are the kind of things you have to
look at at the end of the stage.
You look at what you
think it was going to cost
and what it actually costs.
We're going to put some things in place
to make sure you don't
go over budget either.
We'll talk about those in a future lesson.
The project board is going
to control the project
using this project plan
and those stage boundaries.
Every time we get to a boundary,
that's the chance for the project board
to get involved again and go,
nope, we're done, or yep, continue on.
The project manager's responsible
for updating that project plan and
they're also responsible for running
the day to day execution of the project.
That's all handled by the project manager
and using the manage
by exception principle,
which we're going to talk about next.
(electronic jingle)