- Progress, our last theme
is the progress theme.
And when we deal with the progress theme,
we're worried about
establishing the mechanisms
to monitor and compare
the actual achievements
against those that we plan for.
We want to provide a forecast
for the project's objectives
and the projects continued viability
as well as controlling any
unacceptable deviations.
Now, that's a big, big ask.
Now what does all that really mean?
Well, it means we want to put
into place controls to monitor
and compare what's actually
happened on the project
versus what we thought
should happen on the project
and we also want to look out
into the future to decide
is the rest of the project still on track
and are we going to be successful?
So how do we do all of that?
Well, we're going to use some
effective progress controls.
The first is to delegate authority
from one level of management
downward to the next
and let people deal with the issues
at the lowest level possible.
We're also going to divide
the project up into stages
and authorize them one at a time,
giving us that go-no-go decision point
as we move through the project.
We're also going to have time-driven
or event-driven progress
reports and reviews.
Again, feeding back to those stages
and feeding back to those
products that we expect
to get those go-no-go decisions
and we're also going to raise exceptions
when things aren't going properly
because if you're not
raising the exceptions,
then it's hard for people above you
to delegate authority down to you,
going back to that first point.
Now, all of these project controls
should be documented inside
your Project Initiation Document
because this PID is going to tell you
what is going to occur
throughout the whole project
and the way you're going
to conduct your business.
Now, tolerances are
another important control.
In fact, they are probably one of
the most important controls that's used
inside an effective
PRINCE2 project.
This is your permissible
deviation from a plan
before you have to bring it up
to the next higher authority
and so those exceptions are cruded
based on exceeding tolerances.
So let's start at the bottom.
Let's say you're a team manager
and you're working on a
work package or a team plan,
you are given tolerances
from the project manager.
Now, if they gave you a 2% tolerance
and you exceed that, you
will give a project issue
to the project manager to say
"I exceeded the tolerance."
Now, let's say that that went up to them
and they looked at it and
their tolerance was 3%,
they would give them by the project board
because stage tolerances are
set by the project board.
If we have now exceeded
that stage tolerance,
the project manager has to
create an exception report
and push that up to the
project board to deal with.
Now the project board has
their own set of tolerances
and if we exceed those
project level tolerances,
then they have to put an exception report
up to the corporate or program management
because they're the ones who
set the project tolerances.
And so again, the
lowest, tightest controls
should be down at the work package.
Those mid-grade controls or tolerances
should be at the stage tolerances
and then the widest controls or tolerances
should be at the project level
because as you go up the chain,
you have more responsibility
and more authority
and that's the way that
we can control things
using our tolerances.
Now, there are two types
of progress controls
that I mentioned.
There are time-driven and
event-driven controls.
Time-driven controls are useful
for monitoring and reporting
on time-driven issues.
They're going to occur
at a regular frequency,
whatever that is that you've agreed to.
So for example, maybe your
higher reports are submitted
every two weeks up to the project board.
If that's what you've agreed to,
that is a time-driven control.
Now, if you look at event-driven controls,
these are where you control a
project using a certain event.
This occurs when there's a
specific thing that happens.
So, maybe we're going to lay
the foundation of a house
and then we're going to report that.
Maybe it's when we get the drywall up,
we'll then report that.
Maybe it's when an exception has happened,
then we're going to have to report that
and create an exception report.
These are all examples
of event-driven controls.
So, time is based off the calendar,
event-driven are based
off something that happens
driving us to report it.
Now, inside of the progress theme
there are lots of different
documents we're going to use.
The first is the work
package, or the team plan.
This is authorized by a project manager
before work can actually start.
Next, we have a lessons log
and this is where the lessons learned
are going to be captured
as they're learned
any time we do a review.
That review may come up as
part of an in-stage report
or an in-progress report
or some other forum.
Next, we have a lessons report
and the lessons report is
going to be a collection
of these lessons from the log
and they're going to aid in
our future forecast inaccuracy.
So, if we see that we
are constantly behind
every time we use x-vendor,
maybe we don't want to
use x-vendor anymore.
Next, we have the end stage report
and this is a report that is
written at the end of the stage
to allow that go-no-go decision
to be made by the project board.
This is conducted at
the end of every stage
and it will give us
whether or not the project
is assessed as being viable
to continue if it still
has a valid business case.
And then finally, we have
the end project report.
After you're done with the entire project
and all the stages, you have
to close out this project
and to do that we're going
to use an end project report.
It's conducted at the end to
evaluate the project as a whole
and evaluate whether or not
we can close the project
and if there's any outstanding items.
We'll talk more about
the end project report
when we talk about closing a project
when we get to the processes.
Next, let's talk about our controls
that are used by our project manager.
They're going to use
controls to create baselines.
These controls are things
like the project plan,
the stage plan, the exception
plan and the work package
Because by creating that first product,
they create that first baseline.
Next, we want to talk about how
they can review the progress.
Well, they can review
how the project is going
by looking at the issue
register, the risk register,
the quality register, the
product status account
or the daily log.
All of these help them know
what the current status
and progress of this project is.
Next, they have to
capture and report lessons
and they do that using the lessons log
and the lessons report.
And finally, they have to report progress
and this is done using checkpoint reports,
the highlight report, the end stage report
and the end of project report.
All of these are different controls
that the project manager
uses to keep their thumb
on the pulse of this project
as they move forward.
Now, when we look
at the minimum requirements
for this theme,
there are just a couple of them.
We have to define the projects
approach to control progress.
How are we going to make sure
we progress through the stages?
We also need to create our
Project Initiation Document
because that is a key document
for us to be able to measure
our progress against.
Next, we need to manage by stages
and manage by exception using tolerances.
Both of these were key
principles that we had
that are being implemented
through this theme.
Then, we have to review the business case
whenever an exception is raised.
This is important because
we want to make sure
that the project remains viable.
It's still going to meet the used case
and it's still going to get
the benefits for the customer
at the price, time and quality
and all those factors that
we promised and agreed upon.
And finally, again, we want to learn
from previous lessons in the project
and this is really important
inside the progress area
because in the progress theme,
we're capturing a lot of those lessons
in the lessons report and the lessons log.