- PRINCE2 Foundation.
So what exactly is PRINCE2?
Well, PRINCE2 is a project
management methodology,
and it was first put together back in 1989
under the name, Projects
In Controlled Environments.
PRINCE2 is the evolution of that.
Back in 1996, PRINCE went
through a major evolution
and it became this updated
version known as PRINCE2.
Now it has become the
defacto standard in both
the United Kingdom and
throughout the United Nations.
In 2009, the name was
changed just slightly
as some exam objectives were updated,
and it became Projects In
A Controlled Environment.
Now finally, last year in 2017,
the exam updated once more,
this time to include some Agile
and Development Ops type issues,
and that became PRINCE2 2017,
as you're going to be
tested on on your exam.
Now, do you have to
memorize this whole history?
No, I just wanted to give you
an idea of where it came from.
The big takeaway here is
that PRINCE2 has been around
in some form or another
for about 30 years,
and it's been able to be
evolved through best practices
to make sure that it is a methodology
that's going to perform
well for your organizations.
Now what is PRINCE2 exactly?
Well, it's this methodology,
and it is one of the world's
most popular project
management methodologies.
It focuses on three key areas,
the principles, the
themes, and the processes,
and each of those will
have seven distinct items.
We're going to cover each of those
throughout the next couple of hours.
Now PRINCE2 also is
available to be tailored,
and so, these concepts
from the principles,
the themes, and the processes,
they can all be tailored
to a particular project
regardless of the size,
so if you have a small
project, a large project,
or some project in between,
PRINCE2 can be used
and used effectively, so if
you're doing a large project
like building a skyscraper
that's going to cost
multi millions of dollars, and
it's really, really complex,
PRINCE2 can help with that,
but if you're going to build
a small ecommerce website,
well PRINCE2 can help with that too
because PRINCE2 can be
expanded or contracted
to fit the needs of your organization
and your particular
project, and that's what
tailoring for the
environment is all about.
Now when we talk about
those seven principles,
these are the building blocks
for PRINCE2's methodology.
They are continued business justification,
learn from experience, define
roles and responsibilities,
manage by stages, manage by
exception, focus on products,
and of course, tailor to the environment.
We'll talk about each of
these seven principles
in depth in the next
section of the course.
There's also seven themes, and these are
the project management
areas that have to be
continually addressed during the project,
so from the start of the
project until it's closed out,
you're continually looking at these things
again, and again, and again.
These are things like the business case,
the organization, the quality, the plans,
the risk, the change, and the progress.
And finally, we have the seven processes,
and the seven processes
are going to describe
the who, what, and when of the project.
These are things like
starting up a project,
initiating a project, directing a project,
controlling a stage,
managing product delivery,
managing a stage boundary,
and closing the project
when you're all completed.
Again, we're going to
talk about each of these
three sets of sevens
throughout the rest of
our time together in this course.