- Defined roles and responsibilities.
This is a really important principle
because it's going to ask the question:
Does everyone know what
is expected of them?
Now this is critical
because if I don't know
what's expected of me,
how can I do my job?
And that's what defined roles and
responsibilities is all about.
It's going to ensure that
everyone in the project
knows exactly what role
they're fulfilling,
and the responsibilities associated
with that role.
It's also going to provide them with a
term of reference and role descriptions
for every single team member.
So that if I tell you that your job
is the executive on this project,
you know what that means.
Or if I tell you you're
the senior supplier,
you know what that means.
We'll talk about each
of those roles later on.
Next we also want to ensure
that each team member
has the correct level of authority
to perform their role.
So I want to empower them
to make the decisions
at their level that they
should be able to make.
We'll talk about that
and another principle
called manage by exception.
We also want to ensure that each person
has ample time to dedicate to the project.
I don't know about you,
but I've been at work some days
and I have a million tasks to do.
And if someone says hey
I want you to take on
this new project.
I'm tapped out.
I don't have the capacity or the time
to dedicate to it.
So even if I want to do it and I say
yeah sure make me the
lead on that project.
That project's going to
fail because I don't have
ample time and resources to dedicate
to that project.
So you want to make sure you consider that
as you're defining who has which role
and which responsibility.
Now leadership leads to success.
What do I mean by that?
Well leadership is important.
And when we look at a
project the project manager
is leading that project.
Now how should the organization structure
be built?
Should it be vertical or horizontal?
When I talk about vertical
I'm talking more like
what you see on the left of the screen,
where there's somebody
at the top of the pyramid
and then it kind of flows down from there.
When we talk about horizontal it's more
everybody is going to talk to each other
and to the center project manager
as shown on the right.
Teams are going to be
cross-functional in nature
and everyday organizational structures
usually just don't work.
Because in a project
it's much more based on
relationships than it is on a
strict organizational hierarchy.
So the project manager
is going to be able to
decide how they want to structure
the organization of that project.
Because PRINCE2 doesn't tell you
one way or the other.
There's only a couple of key places
in organization that
PRINCE2 is going to tell you
what you have to do.
And that is a very small vertical part
at the top of the organization.
So when we look at that we have
these management levels.
This is the management hierarchy
that PRINCE2 recommends.
You have a project board that
is at very very top and under them
you're going to have a project manager.
And that project manager has
team managers underneath them.
And so on the screen here you can see
the project board is currently directing
three different projects with a
project manager in charge of each one.
And each of those project managers
has three teams underneath
them working for them.
This is the management hierarchy
that is recommended by PRINCE2.
So it is very vertical in nature
but as a project manager you get to decide
what your organization
is going to look like
underneath you.
What that team looks like.
What the team management looks like.
And what your project looks like.
Only the project board and the
project manager level is really
what's defined by PRINCE2.
Now when we talk about the project board,
the project board is
made up of three people.
It's made up of the executive,
the senior user and the senior supplier.
Now I probably shouldn't
have said three people,
but it's three roles.
There can be multiple
people filling these roles,
with the exception of the executive.
When I talk about the executive
this is the person who's appointed
by the corporation or
by program management
to oversee the project board.
There is only one person who can
be the executive where the other two roles
you can have one or more people
filling those roles.
But the executive he is a singular person
and he has to be that way because
they're going to act as the decision-maker
and have the overall responsibility
for this project that the project board
is overseeing.
They are going to be the one who develop
and own the business case from the outline
all the way through the execution
of this project.
Now a project board is not a democracy.
Each of the other two
roles the senior user
and the senior supplier are
going to make recommendations,
but the executive really
does have the final say.
Because they're the one who is
responsible for this
project and it's success.
Now the senior user is
a role that can be held
by one or more people.
If you're dealing with a small project
the executive can actually
fill this role as well.
Cause if you remember
we talked about PRINCE2
being very tailorable to your environment.
It's a large project you may have
multiple senior users.
If it's a small project you may have
no senior users except for the executive.
Now this role is representing the needs
of the end user who's
going to use the product
that this project is putting out.
This is a liaison between the project team
and the users.
Now when I use the word project team
that's talking about the project board,
these three roles as well
as the project manager.
Those four people together those four
roles together make up the project team.
Now the senior user is going to supply
the benefits review plan.
And in the benefits review
plan it's going to say
these are all the good things we think
that this product is going to do for us.
For example, let's say I wanted to have
an automated log analysis program created.
The benefit for that may
be it's going to save me
hundreds of man hours who are
currently looking through logs.
It's going to identify issues faster.
It's going to solve
problems for me, right?
And it'd be a lot more defined than this,
but you get the idea.
What is it that this program, this app,
this thing, this house that we're building
what are the benefits of it?
In the case of a house
it's going to provide
shelter for somebody.
And it's going to have three
bedrooms and two baths.
It's going to have tile
floors and it's going to have
dry wall that you can hang pictures on.
Whatever those things are,
the benefits review are
going to capture what are
those good things that
we're expecting to get
out of this project?
Now the senior supplier is another role
that can be held by one or more people.
And again in a small project the executive
can fill this role.
So you can see in a small project
we might have a project board of one,
just the executive.
Now this senior supplier is
going to represent the interests of those
who are designing,
developing and implementing
the project's product.
So if we're going back
to that app example,
the senior supplier may be the design team
who consists of the graphics team and the
programming team and the
app development team.
And this person would
represent their interest.
Just like the senior user is representing
the people who are going to use the app,
the senior supplier is representing those
who are building the app.
This is going to provide the supplier
resources for the project.
This is going to be things like people,
tools and expertise.
That's why I said earlier that as
the IT director I was actually a supplier
into many projects.
I gave them what they needed: the people,
the expertise, the server
space, the hardware,
the software, whatever those things were
I was supplying those
as the senior supplier.
Now the senior supplier can come from
within the organization
like a purchasing manager
or the IT director or
it can come from outside
the organization from
the supplier themself.
And this is really common
if you're dealing with
a building project.
So let's say you were going to build
a new office building.
Well there's a lot of different
suppliers you're going to use.
You're going to have
somebody who's going to
build the office building.
You're going to have somebody
who's going to come in
and outfit all the wiring
for the server room.
You're going to have somebody else
who's going to come in
and do all the power.
Another person's going to come and do
all the cooling.
And so you may have representatives
from each of those organizations
each of those suppliers
in your project board
if it's a large enough project.
Now stakeholders.
This is the last person.
And they're not necessarily
on the project board,
but they are represented inside of
the project board.
Now what does that mean?
Well the business, the
users and the suppliers
all have interests that
are being represented
on the project board.
Those are all stakeholders.
PRINCE2 assumes a
customer-supplier relationship.
And when we talk about
who the customer is,
we're really talking about an individual,
a group, or an organization who has
a business need.
So they want to be able
to increase their profits,
they want to cut their
cost, they want to build
a widget or they have some other need.
That's our end customer.
The project is going to build something
for that customer.
So who are the stakeholders?
Those who are building it,
those who are using it,
and those who are dealing with
this project overall.
All of these are stakeholders who
are going to have some
say into the final project
and the final output of that project.
(music tones)