- The seven themes.
So what are themes?
Well themes are these areas of
project management that must
be addressed continuously
throughout the project.
Whether we're initiating the project,
performing the project,
or closing out the project
we still need to address
these seven themes.
Now these themes are based
upon the seven principles.
So you can see on the screen
where I have the seven
principles below and then
on top of that we stack
these seven themes.
These themes are then going
to be applied inside of our
processes that we're going
to get to in the next section
of PRINCE2.
But before we go there we've
got to cover the themes.
And in this section we're
going to cover each of the
seven themes.
Those seven themes are the business case,
organization, quality, plans,
risk, change, and progress.
So let's go ahead and
dive into the themes.