- Congratulations, you've made
it to the end of the course.
Now, I know we've spent
a lot of time together
as we went this PRINCE2 Foundation
Cram to Pass video course.
We've covered the seven
principles of PRINCE2;
those building blocks of
the PRINCE2 methodology,
including: Continued
Business Justification,
Learn from Experience, Defined
Roles and Responsibilities,
Manage by Stages, Manage by Exception,
Focus on Products, and
Tailoring to the Environment.
We then went into applying
those in our themes,
which are project
management areas that had
to continually be addressed
throughout our project,
that include: the Business
Case, Organization,
Quality, Plans, Risk,
Change, and Progress.
We then took those themes and principles
and made them grow legs and start working
for us inside of our processes.
This was where we described
the who, the what,
and the when of our project.
This was our Starting Up a
Project, Initiating a Project,
Directing a Project,
Controlling a Project,
Managing our Product Delivery,
Managing a Stage Boundary,
and Closing out a Project.
Once we did all of that,
where do you go from here?
Well, you've already
watched all the videos,
and you've probably
already downloaded the pdf
with copies of all of
these slides to study from.
But, if you want to test if you're ready
for the final certification exam,
you should take the practice exams.
In this course, I have provided you
with two full-length practice exams
that give you 60 questions each.
When you take those exams,
if you're scoring 70% or higher,
you are ready to take
the PRINCE2 Foundation
Certification Exam for real.
Now, when you go through those exams,
anything you get wrong,
you're going to see
the correct answer and a reason
why the correct answer
was the correct answer.
I want you to go back and
learn from your mistakes,
so that you can get those
questions right the next time.
If you're looking for additional practice,
I do have six additional
full-length practice exams
available for you in our
Practice Exam Only course.
Now, I'm not trying to
sell you something here.
I'm just saying, if you're not doing well
on your practice exams,
take more practice exams.
That can be mine.
That can be some other instructor's.
It doesn't matter.
But, I want you to be ready come test day,
so you can take and pass your
PRINCE2 Foundation Exam
on your first attempt,
because it's pretty expensive to take.
And you don't want to have
to take it more than once.
Now, when you're ready to go take
that PRINCE2 Certification Exam,
you're going to go over to Peoplecert.org
to signup for the exam.
If you want to see how to do that,
I've created a video for you at the end
of this course that will walk you
through how to schedule
and signup for your exam.
And you can take it online
from the comfort of your own home.
So, with that said, I
want you to practice,
practice, practice, and
then go take that exam.
And let me know when you
become PRINCE2 certified.
I hope to see you in a future course,
and good luck.