- Project Management.
So, what is project management?
Well, I mentioned that PRINCE2
is a project-management methodology.
So, we probably should stop and define
what project management is.
Project management is the practice
of initiating, planning,
executing, controlling,
and closing the work of a team
to achieve specific goals
and meet specific success
criteria at a specific time.
Now, that sounds like a lot of words
to explain what is a lot of common sense.
But, having a good
framework and methodology
for project management is going
to help us and our managers know
what we should be doing and
when we should be doing it.
That's really the crux
of project management.
We're trying to be efficient
in doing our projects
so we can save time, save
money, and minimize the risk.
Now, what is a project?
Well, a project is a
temporary organization
that's created for the purpose
of delivering one or
more business products
according to an agreed-upon business case.
We'll talk more about what
a business case is later on.
But, essentially, the key
thing here with a project,
that I want you to take
away is the word temporary.
A project is not everlasting.
A project has a defined
beginning and end state.
So, if I'm going to use the example
of an e-commerce website.
We may have a project
to build the website.
We're going to have to come
up with the creation of it.
We're going to have to code it.
We're going to have to test it,
and we're going to have to field it.
But, once we field it and
we open it for business
for customers to use,
that need to stop being a project
and start being an operation.
So, we're going to
transition this product,
this website, over to
the people who are going
to run it on a daily basis.
Notice, it has a beginning;
and it has an end.
And, that end is defined when we start
back with the agreed-upon business case;
which in this case of a website
may be to provide an e-commerce website
that sells video training courses.
Right?
Once we've done that, we
push it over to operations.
So, keep that in mind.
A project is temporary.
So, I think you understand
why project management is important
and what a project is.
But, why should be even use PRINCE2?
Well, PRINCE2 is a
project-management methodology.
It's going to provide
us with best practices
that have been learned over 30 years,
and we can use to manage
our project using processes.
It can also be combined with things
like the Project Management Professional,
The IT Infrastructure Library, Agile,
and many other methodologies
and frameworks.
It is a mature and proven methodology,
and it's going to provide
us with a common lexicon
or terminology that we can
use to discuss our project
so everyone on the team knows
what we're talking about,
making it easier for us
to accomplish our goal.
Now, when we talk about PRINCE2,
a lot of times people
ask me, "What about PMP?"
because they're both
project-management certifications.
Well, PRINCE2 focuses on what to do.
PMP focuses on how to do it.
So, while PRINCE2 is a
methodology that uses processes;
PMP is more of a standard
and a knowledge base.
These certifications aren't
actually in competition
with each other.
Instead, they can be used with each other
to give you even more benefit.
Now, if you're thinking,
should I get my PRINCE2 certification
or my PMP certification;
one of the things that draws
a lot of people to PRINCE2
over PMP is that it doesn't have
the educational experience requirement.
So, with PMP, before you
can even take the exam,
you have to prove that
you have 4,000 hours
of working on projects.
With PRINCE2, that doesn't exist.
Instead, they have the
foundation-level certification
where you're going to be able
to get some of that experience,
get on to a team, and start working.
And, then you can move up into a PMP.
So, if you're brand new
to project management,
PRINCE2 is a great place to start.
Now, what are some other
benefits of PRINCE2?
Well, like I already
mentioned, it gives you
this common dictionary of terms
for those who are involved in the project.
It also is going to
explicitly state the roles
assigned for each responsibility.
And, we'll talk about that
in the defining roles and
responsibility section.
It's also very customer-focused by design.
PRINCE2 assumes that there
is a customer-supplier relationship.
Now, that doesn't mean
that if the customer
is outside of your
organization necessarily.
For example, I work in the IT field.
I am a supplier to everyone
else in the organization.
I provide them servers.
I provide them databases.
I provide them all different services.
I am the supplier in that relationship.
And, my customer may be
in sales, or marketing,
or accounting.
It doesn't really matter what
department I'm servicing;
I'm still being the service
provider or the supplier
in that case.
PRINCE2 also provides us with
a lot of repeatable processes.
In fact, there are seven processes
that we're going to talk about in PRINCE2
that every project has to go through.
And, if we do it the same way every time,
it becomes very predictable,
and it can reduce our risk.
PRINCE2 also delivers on business needs
because it's very product-based.
It's focused on what the result is.
So, we want to make
sure that, if the result
is we're going to build a website,
then, at the end of this
project, we have a website
that's ready to go and it's
delivered to our customer.
Right?
And, the last thing, is it
adaptable and tailorable
to both the business and
the size of the project?
And, so PRINCE2 has a lot
of benefits for us to use.
But, there's a couple of things
that it won't provide you.
PRINCE2 does not talk
about specialized aspects
of the business.
So, we're not going to talk
about acquisition and procurement.
We're not going to talk
about legal, or financial,
or human resources.
Because, all of those
things are specialized
to your organization;
and they won't be covered
in the generic PRINCE2 framework.
Instead, PRINCE2 is going to leave that
up to your organization
to decide what's best.
It also excludes the management of people.
Now, that may seem weird,
if you come from a
project-management background.
Because PMP is very focused on management
of people, and timelines,
and Gantt charts,
and all of that type of stuff.
But, PRINCE2 doesn't worry about that.
Instead, it focuses on the
products and the processes
to make sure things get done.
They leave the management of people
up to your organization
and the way you organize.
And, it also doesn't
focus on the techniques
or dictate how to do something.
So, for example, PRINCE2 says
you need a business case;
but it doesn't tell you
how you have to write it.
That's left up to you.
Instead, it's more focused on
the process and the products,
the fact that you have a business case;
and that business case is
used throughout the process.
Another example is PRINCE2 says you have
to have a requirement document,
but it doesn't say how to create it,
who you need to talk to
to get it coordinated.
Again, all of that is stuff
that your organization
needs to decide for itself
as it matures its processes
using the PRINCE2 framework.
(buzzing music)