- In this short video,
I'm going to show you
how you can sign up and schedule
your PRINCE2 Foundation exam.
The first step is you're
going to go to peoplecert.org.
This is the official testing
center and it's done online
from the comfort of your own home.
To take the exam online,
you have to have a computer,
an internet connection, a
webcam, and a microphone,
so the online proctor can see you
and hear you during the exam.
Once you go to peoplecert.org,
you're going to scroll down
and you're going to find
where it says PRINCE2.
Once the PRINCE2 Foundation page loads,
you're going to be able to
see the price for the exam.
Now this price does go
by regional pricing.
Depending on where you live in the world,
you're going to see a different price.
In the United States, that
price at retail is $349.
Now, again, depending
where you are in the world
that may be a little bit
less, but it usually is
somewhere between about 315 to $350.
Now you can go ahead and
schedule your exam right here,
or you can save a little bit of money
by taking one extra step.
You can go to diontraining.com
and on the front of our homepage
you'll see the Exam button.
If you click on that Exam button,
what you're going to see is all
of our exam vouchers for sale.
Any of the exams that we
teach, such as ITIL 4, ITIL,
PRINCE2 or PRINCE2 Agile Foundations,
you can go and get your
vouchers through us.
As you can see on the screen,
the current price for
this voucher is $299,
a $50 savings off buying
it through PeopleCert.
Now when you buy it from
us, we're going to collect
your credit card information
and instantly fulfill
that voucher, if it's in
stock, back to your email,
where you'll receive a one time use code.
Once you have that one time
use code in your email,
you're going to go and
click and create an account
by going to the little icon and going down
to Create an account if
you're new to PeopleCert.
If you've taken an ITIL exam
or a PRINCE2 exam before,
you'll actually have an account
and you'll just sign into your account.
Once you go here, you're going to go ahead
and enter your information.
So I'm going to put in Jason Dion.
My email address will be
youremail@youremail.com.
Again, you'll enter in
your own information here.
And then you'll select
your country of residence,
mine is the United States,
and then you'll give it a password.
And you're going to agree to
those terms and conditions
for the privacy and if you'd
like to receive marketing
from PeopleCert, you
can check that as well.
Once you do that, click
on Join PeopleCert.
Now that you're logged in
to your PeopleCert account,
and you have your exam voucher,
you can go and enter
that exam voucher up here
and then click on Confirm.
Once you do that, it will bring
up a date and time calendar
for you to select the day and time
that works best for your schedule.
Once you select that, it'll
show up here under My Exams
and you'll come back here about 30 minutes
before your scheduled time
to be able to sign in,
download the software
needed, and begin your exam.
(electronic music)