- Managing a stage boundary.
So, when we talk about
the managing a stage boundary process,
we're talking about how
we're going to enable
our project manager to
provide the project board
with sufficient information
to be able to review
the success of the
current management stage,
so they can provide
that go, no go decision,
and approve the next stage plan
and review the updated project plan,
confirm that there is still a
valid business justification,
and that they can accept any
risks that are outstanding.
So, when we look at this
on the process timeline,
you can see that it happens
inside the initiation stage
and subsequent stages.
The only stage it doesn't
happen in is the final stage,
because instead of managing
the stage boundary,
we will then close a project,
so you can see where this lies
inside the process timeline.
Let's talk a little bit more about
what managing a stage boundary means.
So, what are the objectives
of managing a stage boundary?
Well, really, here we want
to assure project board
that all the products in the current stage
are completed and approved,
so if I'm developing a piece of software,
maybe there are 10 products
that are going to be created,
and we're going to do
three in the first stage,
two in the second stage, and
three in the final stage.
If I'm coming close to
the end of my first stage,
I need to go prove to the project board
that I've finished the
three pieces of software
for those first three products correctly,
and they've been approved.
Once I have, they'll give me the go ahead
if they think I still
have a valid business case
to move into the second stage.
This is going to allow me, also,
time to prepare for my next stage
by creating the next stage plan.
I also will review and update
my project initiation document
so that we can see if it's still valid
or if there's any changes
that need to be made,
and we're going to
provide the project board
the information needed to verify
that we still have a
continued, valid business case
so that we can get that go decision
and move into the next stage.
If we don't have a valid
business case anymore,
then they should make the decision
to close the project early.
Some other things that we need to do
for managing a stage boundary
is to record any lessons
or information that can
help us during later stages
of this project or another future project.
We also want to request authorization
to begin that next stage, get
that formal go permission,
and then finally, the
other thing we can do
with managing a stage boundary
is get approval for an exception plan,
because maybe we've gotten
off track with this project,
but we think there's still
a valid business case,
and we say hey, here's my exception plan.
I can get us back on track.
If you approve my exception,
I can replace the project plan
or replace the stage plan
and get us back on track
and finish this product successfully.
So, all of this comes
down to getting that go,
no go decision from the project board.
The end stage assessment
here is what happens
at the end of this stage.
That's why it's called the
end stage assessment, right?
It happens near the end of the stage,
and the project manager is going to begin
the managing a stage boundary process.
They're going to make an
assessment of where they are,
what was their forecast,
and what is their actual.
The project manager is going
to meet with the project board
to conduct this assessment,
and they are going to go
over the business case
and the project plan, and
they're going to update those
and provide the most recent
copies to the project board
and say here is where we currently sit.
Here is what I think it's going to take
to get to the next place.
Do you think we're there?
And the project manager has
to present this information
for the project board
so that they can make
an informed decision on the
viability of this project,
and should it get that go decision,
to proceed into the next stage.
The last thing that we have
to do inside this process
is a lessons report.
Every time we get up
to the end of a stage,
we need a lessons report,
and this is going to be
a report that identifies
any lessons that were identified
that can help us prevent issues.
These lessons will be incorporated
into the next stage plan
or an exception plan,
if we got way off track,
and there are going to be
revision to the quality,
the risk, and the issue
management that may be required
based on what we've learned.
Maybe we thought that there
was going to be no snow
as we're building this house,
and there was a big snowstorm
and that took us off track.
Then maybe we need to account
some time in our project
for bad weather days.
This would be a lesson
that we would incorporate
into the next stage plan,
because maybe we're going
into the rainy season,
and that's going to have a work stoppage,
and so you can see what we're doing here.
We're taking these lessons
and incorporating them
back into our stage plan so
our plans get more accurate
and better and more efficient
as we move through the project.
(light tech buzzing)