- Controlling a stage.
So when we look at controlling a stage,
this is the function of
your project manager.
This is going to make sure
that we assign the work
to be done, we monitor that work,
we deal with issues, we report progress
back to the project board,
we take corrective actions
to ensure the stage remains in tolerance.
All of these things are the things
that your project manager
does on a daily basis.
So if we look at this
on the process timeline,
you will see that the controlling
a stage is sitting there
in the managing level.
Managing level is what your
project manager is focused on.
If you look up to the directing level,
that's what your project
board is focused on.
If you look down to the delivering level,
you'll see that that is
what your team managers
and team members are focused on
and we'll talk about that more
in managing project delivery.
But right now, we're talking
about controlling a stage
and this happens in every single stage
starting with the subsequent
stages and your final stage.
Now, as we look at controlling a stage,
there are many objectives.
The first is to ensure the
project management team
is focused on delivery of the product
within the tolerances they were given.
They also want to ensure
that risks and issues
are kept under control
and within tolerances.
You want to ensure that the
business case is being reviewed
to make sure you're delivering a product
that your customer wants,
and you want to ensure that
the agreed-upon products
are delivered within the cost,
effort and time constraints
that you were allotted
by your project board.
Finally, you want to ensure your progress
is being reported to the board
because they're your boss,
they need to know where
you are and you do that
through highlight reports
and when bad things happen
through exceptional reports.
And those have to be escalated up to them
so they can help you get back on track.
Now, when we talk about
controlling a stage,
this is where we're going to conduct
our day-to-day management
by your project manager.
Like I said before, this process is begun
when the project board
approves the project
in the initiation stage.
So once this project gets
started and every time
there's a new stage that
needs to be approved,
that's where this controlling
a stage starts again.
Once you have an approve stage plan,
you're controlling a stage again.
You're going to focus on product delivery
for each stage's products
and any deviations have to be agreed upon
by the project board
before the stage begins,
and approved inside your
project or your stage plan.
The project manager is going
to assign work as work packages
to their team managers to
get the projects delivered.
It's very rare that the project manager,
especially on a large project is going
to be delivering products themselves.
Instead, they're going
to be pushing that down
to their team managers
and those team managers
may even have sub teams underneath them.
Now, all of this has to be reported
and reporting is really crucial.
The team managers are going
to send up checkpoint reports
to the project manager
with their work status.
It looks a lot like a highlight report.
The project managers then collect all
of those progress reports from
all of their different teams
and consolidate them
into an executive summary
called the highlight report.
Using these checkpoint reports,
the project manager can
monitor the schedule
and make sure there's no slippages
that were falling behind schedule
or if we're getting too
far ahead of schedule.
And any kind of cost overruns
should be identified here.
If one is being forecast and
an exception report is required
then it's going to be up
to the project manager
to submit that exception
report up to the Project Board.
Now, once I have an approve stage plan,
it's my job as the project
manager to continually update it
with the progress that I'm
actually seeing inside the stage
and forecast out the
remainder of my stage.
This helps me know where I am in terms
of budget and schedule.
Am I falling behind or am I getting ahead?
Project plans and business cases
are not updated continuously
during this process though.
Those project plans and
those business cases
are going to be updated in
the managing a stage boundary,
and they're going to be
done at the end of the stage
which we talked about in the last lesson.