- Learn from experience.
The next principle we're going to cover is
learn from experience.
And this is really important
because as the old saying goes,
experience is the best teacher.
And PRINCE2 understands that.
So PRINCE2 added this
as one of the principles
you should build your project on top of.
And it really asks the question,
how can we learn from both our
successes and our failures.
Because we learn from both.
When you're successful,
you learn the things
you should be doing.
And when you fail, you learn the things
you shouldn't be doing.
But both of them are very useful.
It's important not just
to learn from yourself
but to learn from others
who have gone before you.
And that's what PRINCE2
really wants to work on,
is capturing that information.
Because it knows that
everyone makes mistakes.
But we need to learn from
them so we don't repeat them.
We do this by collecting
reports of the lessons learned
from previous projects.
So I'm going to start a
new project and I was told
I need to do a rollout of Windows 10,
I might pull the lessons learned
from when we did a rollout
of Windows 8.1 or Windows 7 or Windows XP,
because they're very similar experiences.
Now maybe one department has
already done the rollout.
So I might learn from them
exactly what they did and
what went right and what went wrong.
Now as a project manager,
I want to make sure that
I'm generating reports
during my project as well.
So I'm capturing those
lessons while they're fresh
in my mind.
And that way, they could be passed out
to other project managers so
they can learn from as well.
So, whose responsibility is
capturing all these lessons?
Well, the project manager
should be the one to identify,
document and disseminate the
lessons via the lessons report
up to the project board who oversees them.
That project board though,
oversees a lot of projects.
And so it's their job to
take that information and
pass it down to other project
managers to implement inside
of their projects.
And so we have this
pyramid and this triangle
of passing information up,
over and down so that everyone
can learn from each other
as we move through and
do project management.
Now, the big things to remember
is that hindsight is 20/20.
What do i mean by that?
Well, it's really easy to
look back on a project and go,
man if only we didn't do X,
we wouldn't have had
this bad thing happen.
Well, it's easy to see
that when you look back.
But it's hard to figure
it out in the future.
And so you want to make
sure that you're capturing
these things as they happen
and after they happen.
So you don't repeat them in the future.
The way you do this is by
setting up a lessons learned log
during the starting up a project process,
which we'll talk about later.
You also want to generate lessons
at the end of each stage and
pass those lessons reports
up to the project board.
And then, the final lessons
learned report is going to be
created during your
closing a project process.
Because as you close that
project, you want to capture
anything that happened
during the project as well as
the process of closing the project itself.
Because sometimes, closing a project has
just as many problems as doing the project
during the middle of the cycle.
Now, lessons learned are testable.
What do I mean by that?
Well if your company follows PRINCE2
from an auditing perspective,
and they have assurance
auditors coming in to check
and see if you're compliant
with PRINCE2, they will ask
for evidence that lessons
are actually being learned
and not just collected.
I've been in a lot of organizations
where we really just call
them lessons observed.
We see this problem in a
project, we write it down and
then we forget about it.
And then we do the project
again, very similar,
and we have the same problems.
Because we didn't learn our lessons.
So these auditors are going
to be looking for proof
that the things you noted that
were bad have actually been
implemented to improve the process and
prevent mistakes in the future.
So I want you to remember
that lessons learned
are not the same as lessons observed.
You need to take action.
You need to implement those
changes so you're not repeating
the same issues from the previous project
in your new project.
You learn from those things,
change and continually improve.
So how do we prevent mistakes?
Well the first things is we have to learn
from those past mistakes
like we mentioned,
to prevent new ones from occurring.
We also want to create a repository
of these lessons reports.
So as the project manager, I'm
going to turn my report in up
to the project board.
But that's not where it should stop.
They should go into some sort
of an electronic database or
a collection system like a
SharePoint site or other,
so that other people can
search and find things
about this project that may
relate to their project.
You also want to recruit
member to your project
with similar project experience.
Because there really is no
substitute for experience.
Now I deal with a lot of people trying
to get into the cybersecurity world.
And they get really upset
because they're like,
no one will give me a chance
because I don't have experience
in this job, they won't give me a job
so I can get experience.
And I get that, it's very frustrating.
But you have to look at
it from their perspective.
They're trying to minimize
risk in their projects and
in their operations.
And the way that you do that
is by finding qualified people
who have experience and
have done that thing before.
Because if you've done that thing before,
you're less likely to have mistake
because you know what you're doing.
And that's kind of the idea here.
If I'm going to go and
put on the Olympic games,
I want to get people who worked
on the last Olympic games right?
If I'm going to go build an
app, I want to get people
who have built apps before, not
somebody who's built houses.
Now some of those skills will transfer
from project to project.
But a lot of it is based on
the industry you work in.
And so finding people who have experience
in that type of a thing is very useful and
something you should be looking for
to help you prevent mistakes.