- Starting up a project.
So when we start up a project,
we are trying to ensure
that the prerequisites for
initiating this project
are in place by answering
one simple question.
Do we have a viable
and worthwhile project?
And that's really important,
because as you look at
our process timeline here,
you will see that starting up
a project occurs in the pre-project phase.
This is the cheapest
place for this to occur.
We start with this starting up a project
to determine is it worthwhile
to start dedicating the time,
the money, the man
hours, and the resources
into this project.
And so, we're going to
start way early here
and determine if we
should even move forward.
Now, as we look at the
objectives of starting up
a project, the first
couple things we have to do
is get some man hours behind it.
We need to appoint those
who are going to work on it
during the initiation stage.
Now at this point, we haven't decided
if this is a worthwhile project yet,
we are just going to put in
minimal hours and minimal manpower
to determine if it's a good idea.
We're going to appoint significant
project management roles,
so people like the executive
should be defined right now.
And the reason why, is the
executive has to be the one
to show that this good idea
is going to make a worthwhile
business case for us to implement.
We also need to create
an initiation stage plan,
and we do that once we get later into the
starting up a project phase
because we've determined
that it may be a good idea
and we should move forward.
And the initiation stage is
based on sound assumptions.
We have to define things like
the scope of the project,
how long it's going to
take or the timescale,
the acceptance criteria, What
will the finished product
look like that people would like,
and the constraints.
What are we going to say
are the limitations around
this project?
Maybe we have a limitation
that we're not going to spend
more than 100 manhours or 100,000 dollars,
or whatever it is.
Those constraints have
to be known up front
so we can decide is
this project worthwhile.
And all of that starts
with this project mandate.
Now our goal here is simple.
We want to take the hundreds
of ideas that come up
in a daily meeting, and
decide which one is the one
viable project idea that we
should move forward with.
Because I don't know about you,
but when I go to meetings and
we have a brainstorming meeting,
people throw all sorts
of crazy ideas up, right?
That's kind of the
purpose of brainstorming.
But you might have 50,
or 100, or 200 ideas,
but you only have enough
resources to implement one or two
of them.
So we want to only initiate the project
that might be successful
and discard all of the rest
before we waste a lot of
time, money, and resources.
So just as you see here on the screen,
I have five different ideas,
but only one is going to
turn into that end product.
And that's the goal here
with starting up a project.
And we do that by starting with a mandate.
The project mandate is your
trigger for the project.
This comes from the
customer's organization,
and it can come from their
corporate, program management
office or from the customer themself.
They can just say, you
know, it'd be really great
if I had X product, and now
you've got a project mandate
to work with, right?
This is going to provide
the reason for undertaking
the project and it's going to
identify the proposed executive.
At this point, when you
get a project mandate,
this says I think it'd be a
great idea if we had a new
travel system, and I'm
going to dictate that Jason
is going to be the executive for it.
That's pretty much as
deep as you might get on
a project mandate.
If you're lucky, they may
give you a one or two page
description of what they think
this travel system will be.
But you're not always that lucky.
Sometimes it's as easy,
and a small project,
as somebody going I have this idea,
go forth and conquer, right?
If it's a large project,
it'll be a little bit more
formalized.
But once you get this project mandate,
that's what's going to
trigger the starting up a
project phase, or process,
that we're going to work through here.
Now, when you're inside the
starting up a project process,
you have a couple of requirements.
You have to identify key
roles and responsibilities
for who is going to take this
thing forward if it's greenlit.
If someone says go into the next stage,
which is the initiation stage,
who's going to do that work?
So that's identifying those
key board members, right?
And who's going to be the project
manager and things like that.
You're also going to have
to allocate resources.
So if it gets beyond a project mandate,
and you are told to start up the project,
somebody's got to fund it because
this is going to start taking
man hours, it's going
to start taking money,
it's going to start taking equipment,
and it's going to start taking time.
And you have to identify who's
going to write the business
case and the project plan.
Normally, this is going
to be your project manager
or your executive.
Remember, the executive is
responsible for the business case
but it doesn't mean
they're going to be the one
sitting down to write it.
Now, when we talk about the business case,
this is going to explain
how the project fits
into the customer's objectives
and how it's going to be funded.
The executive is responsible
for securing that funding.
So this is their baby, they
have to champion for it.
They have to convince the
stakeholders and the customers
and the suppliers that they
should all get on board
with this.
And the executive is
responsible for creating
the outline of that business case,
and then they can turn
that over to somebody else
to write the full business case for them.
Now, the outputs of
this stage are two-fold.
You have to have a project brief.
This is going to ensure the
project has the agreed upon
and well defined starting point.
So everybody knows what
your end product is going to
look like.
And you're going to brief that
to those key stakeholders.
You're also going to have to
create an initiation stage plan.
Remember, we don't need the
entire project planned out yet.
We just need the next stage.
So we're going to do that with
the initiation stage plan.
This is going to cover all the
work that's going to be done
in the initiation stage,
which we'll talk about
in the next lesson.
As well as the project
manager is going to review
the lessons log for
projects that look similar,
so that they can use those
controls inside of the
initiation stage itself, as well.
Now, that is what we're talking
about when we talk about
starting up a project.
In the next lesson,
we're going to talk about
directing a project.
And then, we're going to move
into the initiation stage.