- Quality. Our third theme is Quality.
When we talk about quality,
this about defining
and implementing the
mechanisms in the project
to determine if your products
going to be fit for purpose,
and be able to provide those benefits
that the customer is expecting.
This asks the question does the product
meet the agreed upon requirements?
Because if it doesn't,
you're not meeting the
quality your customer expects.
Now to do that we come up
with acceptance criteria.
Acceptance criteria is
the measurable definitions
of attributes of a set of products
that makes them acceptable
to the key stakeholders.
Now that's a lot of legalese type jargon,
that really says if you told the customer
you were going to deliver something
that went from zero to 60 in three seconds
and you brought them
something that went zero to 60
in five seconds, that didn't
meet the acceptance criteria.
So you have to meet what you promise them.
This is agreed upon before
the project ever begins,
that way everyone knows
what is expected of them
and what the outcome of
this project is going to be.
Most customer requirements
though are pretty vague,
and so you need to work with them
to make sure that you develop
good acceptance criteria.
When I used to build websites
I used to hear all the time
"I want things, I want it
faster, I want it cheaper,
I want it more user friendly."
What does that really mean?
So when they want something
that says "I want it faster,"
I would say "Okay, we want
to make sure your load time
is less than two seconds."
I want it cheaper. Okay,
it's currently costing you
a hundred thousand dollars a year,
we're going to build you something
that's only going to
cost you $80,000 a year.
And if we can meet those
metrics, they're measurable,
it takes all the guesswork out of it,
and the acceptance goes much easier
at the end of the project.
You want to make sure you
document this acceptance criteria
in your high-level requirements documents.
So everyone, before the
project is initiated,
signs off on it and knows
what they're agreeing to.
You want to describe
this in measurable terms,
and so know what the
product can be delivering,
and make sure that at the
end we can meet those things.
Because if at any time
we think we can't meet
that end acceptance criteria,
the project could be canceled.
Which is okay, sometimes it's a good idea
to cancel a project and
start it again later,
or just pivot to a different direction.
Now when we're talking
about the Quality Theme,
you've got to consider what is going to be
your Quality Management Approach.
Your Quality Management
Approach is going to help you
to document the method of quality control
that you're going to
use inside your project.
The Project Manager is
ultimately responsible
for quality planning,
and he's document this
inside the Quality Register.
All along the way he's going
to be doing quality checks
to make sure the project is on track
and meeting the things it's supposed to.
Now the organization is going to have
a Quality Management System that contains
your quality policies,
procedures, and standards
expected within your organization.
And that's going to apply
across all projects.
Quality Assurance is
an organizational role.
It's somebody outside of your project.
And they are going to be
looking at your project
and everyone else's projects
to make sure that they are following
the Quality Management System.
They're going to make sure
those projects are in compliance
with the organizational policies,
procedures, and processes
to make sure that it
can pass quality audits.
So when we look at Quality Assurance,
it sounds a whole lot like
the Project Assurance role
we talked about in the
Organizational Theme,
but it's not, they are
two separate things.
Quality Assurance role is
external to your project,
it's somebody in the organization
not inside your Project
Board or Project Team.
Their main function is to
assure corporate management
or the program level board
that your project is complying
with corporate standards,
policies, and procedures.
The Project Assurance role,
the one we talked about
in the last lesson in
Organizational Theme,
is internal to your project.
It's somebody that's
assuring the Project Board,
that senior user, senior
supplier, and the executive,
that your project is
being conducted properly.
So you can see this
internal versus external.
Again, lots of checks and balances
throughout this project management,
because we're talking about large projects
that cost lots of money.
We want to make sure
that if we're spending
a million dollars on our project,
it's going the way we want
and it's providing the right quality
that our organization expects.
Now when we look at Quality Assurance
we also look at what's
called Quality Control.
Quality Assurance is focused on how
the processes actually
work, not the end product.
Quality Control is more
focused on the end product.
They want to verify that
the product you build
is fit for purpose.
So if I'm building a car,
Quality Assurance says my
procedures to build the car
are of high quality, they're working well.
Quality Control says
that the air conditioning
actually works, the radio
turns on, the car starts up,
and that the tires aren't flat.
You can see the difference there.
Now Quality Control is
also going to maintain
your quality and assurance records,
and they're going to help you gain
the acceptance of your product
at the end, by the end customer.
Because again, if the thing
is not fit for purpose,
your customer doesn't want to accept it,
and then you're stuck holding the bag.
So you got to make sure you
work through these things
and keep your quality high.
Now your Quality Records are
going to be these documentation
of your quality tests.
They're going to contain all the details
of the results of these quality tests.
Your product is judged
based on its ability
to be fit for purpose, based
on these quality tests.
Now how many tests do you need?
Well, that's up to your project manager.
They are going to build that
into their quality plan,
and based on this fit for purpose testing
the product is then going
to get approved or not,
and if it is an approval
record will be created.
Now what is an approval record?
Well it's just a formal
or informal document
saying that this product met
the level of quality required.
That may take the form
of a printed document
with formal signatures or
it could just be an email
from one boss to another
saying we accept it,
we take ownership now, we agree that
it passes the quality test.
So this really depends
on your organization
and the level of project.
Smaller projects will have informal,
larger projects will have formal.
That just depends on the way
your organization sets it up though.
Next we have the baseline.
And once you approve a product,
it becomes your baseline,
effectively version 1.0.
Now at this point, once
we've created version 1.0,
everything else becomes a change
that has to go through the
change management process,
and it's going to go through
change control and versioning.
Users will submit what's called an RFC,
or a Request for Change, and
that way it can get approved
and funding can be applied
to make any changes or alterations.
Again, very common in the software world,
you may think it's not as
common in the physical world,
but it really is.
You look at a car, there's a version one,
and there may be a version 1.1
because they found out that
an airbag wasn't quite right
and they wanted to change those out
with a different product.
Or if you have a house,
they build the whole house
and go you know what I think that pantry
could've been three feet bigger,
and they can tear down a wall
and move the wall three feet,
and now you've got a bigger pantry.
You're now at version 1.1 of your house.
That's the idea, it's any
changes to these baselines
for this product once
it has been approved.
Now we talked about what happens
when quality is approved
and you pass your test,
but what if you fail your test?
What if your product is not
considered fit for purpose?
Well then the supplier has to
continue to build the product
until they can meet the
level of quality required.
The product is not going to be accepted
until it meets that level of quality
that was agreed upon all the
way back at the beginning
based on our acceptance criteria.
Now what do you do if you can't reach
that level of quality that's needed?
Maybe we agreed that our iPhone
should be able to be dropped
from a two foot distance from the floor
without cracking the screen.
And we go to do our test and we find
that we just can't make that happen.
We would need new glass,
or a new technology
that just doesn't exist yet.
Well, we can go back to the project board
and say we can't meet the requirements.
Either we need you to
change the requirements,
and change it from two feet to one feet,
or we are going to have
to stop the project
'cause we're just never
going to get there.
And that will be a determination
that the project board
and program management or
corporate management can make.
They can make the
requirements less stringent,
making it go from two feet to one feet,
or they can give you more money
and say "What if I give you
another million dollars,
can you make the technology then?"
Maybe you could.
Or they could say "You
know what, if you can't
meet two feet, forget it,
the whole project's off."
And they will terminate the project early.
Those are your three options.
You either throw more
money at the problem,
you make it less of a specification,
or you just stop the project completely.
Now all of these things
have to be documented.
And when you pass an acceptance test,
you're going to put that
into an acceptance record.
That record is the formal acceptance
of the final product by
different stakeholders.
This will be formal, it
will be in the project
as we go through all of
the acceptance criteria
and verify that we've met them.
All of your acceptance
methods should be determined
before your project begins,
so we all know what the
finish line looks like,
and it's documented inside your
Quality Management Approach.
Now, as far as PRINCE2 is concerned,
there are a couple of
things you have to do
at a minimum to be able to
check off your Quality Theme.
So the first thing you have to do
is define your Quality
Management Approach,
and that's going to cover
your quality control
and your project assurance.
Remember, quality control
and project assurance
happen inside the project.
Quality assurance happens
outside the project.
You also need to make sure you define
your roles and responsibilities,
like who is doing your project assurance,
who is going to do your quality assurance,
and what are the
responsibilities for those.
You also need to create Quality Records
and a Quality Register, which is the way
you document quality
throughout the project.
You're also going to
make sure your customer
has quality expectations
and acceptance criteria
defined in your product descriptions
before you initiate this
project and move forward,
because I can't start building the things
if I don't know what I'm building towards.
And finally, you should
look back at other projects
and look at the lessons that they learned,
and so you can incorporate those
into your quality planning.
Because if I built a phone before,
and I couldn't meet a two
foot drop requirement,
I need to figure out that, maybe,
that requirement needs to be less,
before I start going down
that road trying to meet it,
or I may need to find new technologies.
Those lessons learned
are going to be critical
to helping you maintain
a high level of quality
and meet those requirements.