- Continued business justification.
So, continued business
justification is the first principle
we're going to look at.
Continued business justification
asks one simple question:
Are the benefits still worth
the risks and the cost?
So when we look at a project we need
to determine if it is.
If it meets those two
criteria, we should continue
with that project.
If it doesn't, then we
probably shouldn't continue
and we should close the
project down instead.
So let's look a little bit deeper
into continued business justification.
First, the project must
always remain desirable,
viable, and achievable.
Let's break that down.
What's desirable mean?
Well, if a project is desirable
it's asking the question,
are there going to be
positive balance of benefits,
costs, and risks.
Are we going to get more
good out of this project than
the money or resources
it's going to cost us,
or the risk that it puts
our organization into.
Next, we want to look at viable.
Is the project going to be viable?
That asks the question
can the organization have
the capability to deliver those products.
So if I take my organization for example,
we're an online training business.
Students pay us for us to teach them
how to pass an exam.
That's something that we're
good at and we can do,
we have the capability to do that.
But, if somebody tried to hire
us to go build a skyscraper,
I would have to turn that project down.
Because it's not what I'm good at,
it's not what I'm designed to do.
It's not viable for my company to do that.
And so that wouldn't be a good fit for us.
So your project should
always remain desirable,
viable, and thirdly, achievable.
So when we talk about a
project being achievable
we're really asking, will
the use of the project's
products result in the
outcomes and benefits
that are expected?
Now you may be wondering,
why is there an Olympic logo
here on the screen.
Well, the Olympics is
an example of a project
and it happens every four years.
The Olympics were put
together so that countries
could come together into
a neutral area and compete
on the sports field.
And so we could see
who's the fastest runner,
or the fastest swimmer, or
the best basketball player.
And it allows all the
countries to come together
to do somethings that's
competitive but not threatening,
like a war might be.
The outcome of that is supposed
to be good will towards
our fellow man, now, does
that project achieve that?
Is it worth all the
money to get the outcome
of those Olympic games?
Well, apparently the Olympic
Games Committee believes it is
because they keep funding
it every four years
and continue to do that.
So, for them, it's something
that they think is achievable.
The outcome of that
project, the games themself,
brings entertainment and joy
to millions around the world.
Now, when I look at continued
business justification
we have to ask the question, what do we do
if we aren't going to have
a project that's desirable,
viable, and achievable?
And notice when we talk
about continued business
justification, we're talking about this in
a continuous manner.
Throughout the project not
just to start the project
because to start it, obviously
we think it's desirable,
viable, and achievable.
But, if we get six months
down the road in this project
and we still aren't on track
to finish it we may go,
"It's no longer desirable,
viable, or achievable,
"and instead we're going
to close the project."
My aunt is a realtor down in Florida,
and back in 2008, 2009, 2010
timeframe, there were a lot
of houses that were
being left half finished
just like this because those neighborhoods
and those subdivisions
that were being built,
they realized that it
was no longer a desirable
or viable project for them.
Because, the housing market dried up.
There wasn't enough money
and enough buyers to buy
these new houses that were
being built on speculation.
And so a lot of construction just stopped
and houses sat there
like this for six months,
twelve months, years at a time.
And now, in 2018, a lot
of that inventory has been
bought up and has been resold.
But back then you would
see lots of neighborhoods
that just sat there, half
finished like this house
on the screen because those projects,
they simply closed them.
They left them where
they were and decided,
were not going to put
anymore money down this road
because we're not going to see
a return on that investment.
Now, another thing we look when we look
at continued business
justification is the return
on investment, like I
was just talking about.
This is going to prevent
us from wasting resources
on a project that has no benefit.
But I want to caution you,
benefits are not only monetary.
There are other things out there.
So, you may be doing something
that is going to give goodwill
towards your company, or a
better brand recognition,
or something else of
value to your company.
It doesn't necessarily
have to be that I put
a hundred dollars in to
get two hundred dollars out
in return on investment.
I may put a hundred dollars
in so that I have more
brand recognition and that
may be more important to me.
So, whatever that project is,
you're going to define that in
your business case, up front,
so you know what the end
output is supposed to be.
And if you're going to
be on track to meet that,
the project will be continued.
And that brings us to the
concept of a business case.
I just mentioned that
before you start a project,
you have to have a valid business case.
That way you can see if you can have a
continued business
justification by comparing
it back to this business case.
Now a business case is a
product that is developed
to provide the justification.
It also is a theme, and we'll
talk about it in the theme
section as well.
An initial business case is an outline
that's developed during
the pre-project phase
to determine if the project
should even be initiated.
So, some executive has
a great idea and says,
"You know what, we should build an app."
So they go ahead and build
a justification for that
in a business case.
They'll say, "Well, we're
going to build an app,
"and it's going to do
one, two, three functions
"it's going to cost us x-amount of dollars
"and take us y-amount of time."
And they'll present that to
try to get funding for it
so they can move forward
and initiate the project.
This, then would be fully developed during
the initiation stage.
So, once the CEO or the
head leadership goes,
"Yes, I think building
an app is a great idea,
"I approve of your business case,"
they then, will flush that out further
and give more details during
that initiation stage.
And this will also be continually updated
throughout the project to make
sure it continually remains
viable and achievable as we
work through the project.
So, do I need a business
case for everything?
Well, yes.
You need a business case
even if your project is
compulsory, regulatory, or
required by some executive.
You still are going to create
a business case because
it gives justification to your project
and throughout the project
we're going to go back
and compare it against
the business case to make
sure that it still remains
achievable and viable.
There's always more than
one way to solve a problem,
and therefore, you're going to give your
executives some choices.
And we usually call
those, courses of action.
So I will come up with
two or three, or four ways
that I can solve a
problem and then we'll let
management decide which
way we're going to go
by using this business case.
So let me give you an example.
Let's say my company decided
we wanted a way to test
students and see if they're
retaining the information.
Well I can do that by
providing an online quiz,
or I can use an online survey,
or I can give you a PDF
that you can download
and fill out and then Email back to me.
There's lots of ways to do it.
But I'm going to come up
with a business case of,
I'm going to build an app
for iPhones that's going to
allow you to do that quiz.
Right, I now have to justify
how much it's going to cost.
What the timing is, and
if it's actually going to
have value for my customer.
And if it doesn't, we
wouldn't do it, right?
That's the idea of a business case.
So what kinds of things
are covered inside of a
business case?
Well, a business case
has six key components.
There's the reason for the project,
why are we going to do this?
In the case of my app, I want
students to be able to take
practice exams and see how they're doing.
Expected benefits and dis-benefits.
What does that mean?
Well, there's good things that happen,
those are the benefits.
But, there's bad things that happen.
Those are dis-benefits.
What threshold would make you want
to terminate the project?
Every project has good
things and bad things
and you have to figure out what those are.
And you'll list them
in your business case.
You'll also have a timeline,
the cost, and risks
associated with the project.
You'll have underlying assumptions.
So, if I'm doing an app
for instance, I may make
the underlying assumption
that 75% of my customers
use iPhones, and therefore,
we should release
an iPhone version first.
Now, that's an assumption.
It may be completely wrong,
and if we start launching it
and we see, whoa, we're
not getting the traction
we thought we were going
to, maybe it's because
one of my assumptions was wrong.
There also has to be options considered.
So, I might say, "We're
going to do this project
"and we're going to do iPhones first,
"but we also thought about doing Android
"and we also thought about doing Windows
"and we also thought about
doing a web-based version,"
"but we went with iPhone
because of x, y, and z reasons."
That's what we're going to
cover here in the business case.
And then we're going to give
them the chosen solution.
In my case, we went with
iPhone first because
we decided that was where we thought
75% of our customers were.
So you can see how this business case
starts coming together and
when you put it all together
here early in the stage,
it's just an outline.
It's very, very short.
Just a couple of pages usually.
But again, that's going to be
dependent on your organization
and the way that they like
to get their business cases.
(electronic music)