- Risk.
So, the next theme we're
going to talk about is risk
and when we concern ourself
with the risk theme,
we're thinking about how
we can identify, assess
and control uncertainty
and improve the ability
of the project to be successful overall.
Because in everything
we do, there is risk.
Now, what exactly is risk?
Well, risk is an uncertain event
which will have an effect
on the project's objectives
and that objective is to produce
the final product, right?
And so when we look at this,
we have to consider two
major pieces of this risk,
the uncertain event piece.
That means the event may or may not occur.
When we're dealing with
risk, it is uncertain.
We don't know if it's going to happen.
If it does happen, then
it may become an issue.
But until it does, it's
just this uncertain future
that's out there.
It may or may not happen.
There's a risk that when
I go to work tomorrow,
I could get hit by a car.
That may or may not happen, right?
That's what we're talking
about here, this risk.
And the second piece is the effect.
Now most of us think
of risk as negatively.
There's a negative effect that can happen,
like I could get hit by a car tomorrow
but there's also positive risk.
What if I found $20 on the street?
There's a risk that may happen
and I'll get $20 extra, right?
There is positive and
negative risk out there.
And we'll talk about that as
we go through this lesson.
Now, risk is not a project issue.
And what I mean by that
is that there are these
things called project issues.
These are an event that have happened
and they weren't planned for.
So if I was building a house
and someone was laying tile in my bathroom
and I hired them to lay that tile
and they brought the wrong tile
and laid it all out and spent two days
of work putting the new
tile in the bathroom,
that would be a bad thing, right?
That's an issue.
There was a risk they would
have brought the wrong tile,
and in this case, that risk was realized.
That turned into a project issue
and now we need to rip out
all that tile and redo it
and it's going to cost us
more time and more money.
Risk, on the other hand,
is this uncertain event
that is in the future.
It may or may not happen,
as we just talked about.
And when a risk occurs, it
could become a project issue.
Sometimes they are, sometimes they're not.
If there was risk that we had
an additional customer load,
where more customers bought
our product than we expected,
that may not be a bad thing
and so it wouldn't be a project issue.
But if too many people,
and there was millions of people
who came to our website
that we're building,
and we weren't expecting that,
that could actually crash our server.
And so too much acceptance of our product
could be a bad thing as well.
And so you really have to weigh this thing
and think about the risk
and what you can do to minimize the risk
and have a positive
impact for you overall.
Now, when we look at this, we
talk about realizing the risk.
And realizing the risk
is when the risk happens.
There are threats and
there are opportunities.
Now those negative things
we're talking about,
those are all threats.
And those threats is when risk is realized
through a negative impact.
Something bad happens.
We installed the wrong tile.
We crashed our server.
There was a vulnerability that was found.
All those things are threats.
But we also have opportunities
and these are the good things that happen.
This is when risk is realized
with a positive impact.
So, I thought I was only going
to get 100 customers the
first day but I got a 150.
It was enough that I could
handle the extra load
but I made a bunch of extra money.
That's a good thing.
Now, if I had 100,000 show up on day one,
that may become a threat cause
it could crash the server.
And so you can see how these
risks could go positively
or could go negatively.
And it really depends
on how you handle them
and how your project is
setup to handle these risks.
And that takes us to this
concept of a risk budget.
When you're building out your
financials for your project
and how much it's going to cost,
you should have a dedicated pot of money
that's used to fund any risk responses.
That's called the risk budget.
Going back to the house building example,
if the project manager
didn't catch the tile
before it was installed,
they would now have to
pay to take out the tile,
to buy new tile and to install that tile.
Those three things may
cost them another $1,000.
That would come from the risk budget
because it wasn't planned
and that risk was realized.
The guy put in the wrong tile.
Now, how much risk
you're willing to accept
is really a question
for your organization.
And we measure this in something
called the risk appetite.
Some organizations are very risk adverse
and they will not take any risk at all
or take very minimal risk.
Other organizations
will take a lot of risk
and they have a very high risk tolerance
or high risk appetite.
Now, that risk tolerance is
the threshold that is set
that cannot be exceeded without
an exception being written
in the exception report.
Now again, depending on your organization,
they may be more or less risk adverse.
And the way you overcome
some of that adverse risk
is that you start planning for it
and you come up with mitigations
to bring the risk level down.
Other organizations will
just accept the risk
and they'll just say that's
the cost of doing business.
These are the things that your
organization's going to have
to determine and you're
going to have to live within
those frameworks and that risk tolerance.
Now, how is your project
going to deal with risk?
Well, that's where the risk
management approach comes in.
And this is a written outline
of your risk management
and it is required as you
initiate your project.
There's going to be a document
called the risk management approach.
It will tell you what
your risk tolerance is,
how much budget you're going to have
and how you're going to deal
with risks that come up.
All of your risks should be identified
in what's called the risk register
which is a document or a journal
that the project manager's going to own.
This is going to document every
single risk in the project
and it's going to be used
by the project manager
to capture these risks
and notate how they're
going to handle those risks
if they are realized and become an event.
Now, as a project manager
or someone working on the project,
you're going to have to deal with risk.
And the way we do that is
through a five step procedure.
We identify the risk, we assess the risk,
we plan for the risk, we
implement our risk mitigations
and then we communicate those risks upward
to either the project manager
or up to the project board.
So when we deal with identifying it,
these are where we're going to list out
our threats and opportunities.
We're going to describe them
in terms of their source,
the event or the area of uncertainty
that may happen and the effect or impact.
Being able to identify all those things
that might go wrong or
possibly could go right,
that are risky for us, is
a really important step.
Then, we're going to take that
list of all of those risks
and we're going to assess them.
We're going to estimate the probability
or the likelihood, the
impact, the proximity,
when it's likely to occur,
and evaluate all the net overall effect
of all of these risks.
So if you're building a house
or an apartment building,
there are lots of bad
things that can happen
and lots of good things that can happen.
We're going to list all those out
and assess which ones are
most likely to happen.
Is it very likely that someone
is going to install the wrong fixtures?
Probably.
Is it very likely or less
likely that the house
will burn down during construction?
Probably less likely.
And as we go through all of these things,
we're going to figure out how we can plan
for those risks, starting
with the most likely
and moving our way down
to the least likely.
And that brings us into
our planning stage.
When we plan, we're going
to curve for one or more
of those specific risks
and figure out what our responses may be.
So now that we've planned,
we have to implement that
and this is where we're
going to take action
in response to our chosen risk.
So we're going to pick one
of those risks from the list,
we've assessed it and we
planned a counter measure to it,
something to mitigate it.
Now, we're going to implement it.
So let's take the example
of your installing a new
work station into a network.
It's a very small project.
There's risk associated with that though
because as you install
that new workstation,
you might be bringing in
additional vulnerabilities.
Well, one of your mitigations may be
to institute a vulnerability
management program
and scan those workstations
before they're installed.
This is a mitigation to lower your risk
that you're going to be
bringing into your network.
And you're going to do this
by assigning a risk owner
who's going to be be
responsible for managing
this vulnerability management program,
this risk of bringing in the new machines,
and a risk actionee
who is going to carry
out the risk response,
the person who's going to run
those vulnerability scans.
So you can see how you have this risk,
you have this mitigation,
and somebody who's
responsible for both of those.
Next, we're going to look at communicate.
And this is where we
want to report the status
of the risk up to your shareholders
using your PRINCE2 reports,
such as your Highlight reports
or your Exception reports.
So if there was a risk
and it was realized,
you better communicate that
up and what you did about it.
Or, if there's some big risk
and you think you need more
money to your risk budget
to be able to put in implementations
and mitigations for it,
then again, you're going to
have to communicate that up.
And if it's outside your
budget and your tolerance,
it's going to be an exception.
If it's within your tolerance
and within your budget,
it would just be inside
your Highlight report.
Now as we go forward, we
can talk about the two types
of risk responses.
We have responses to threats
and we have responses to opportunities.
Remember, threats are
those negative things.
When we look at risk, we can avoid it.
We can reduce it.
We can accept it.
We can transfer it.
We can share it.
And we can prepare contingency
plans to deal with it.
Now, when we look at the positive side,
we can exploit it.
We can enhance it.
We can reject it.
We can transfer it.
We can share it
and we can prepare our contingency plans.
Now, wait a minute.
The last three in both of
those columns are the same.
That's right.
And this makes it really easy on test day.
So you just need to remember
what are the threats and the opportunities
and look at them of what is different.
Because they may give you a question
that says something like
what is not an appropriate
risk response to threats?
And then they'll say something like
avoid, reduce, accept,
transfer, share and reject.
You go, "Ah, wait a minute.
"Reject is an opportunity."
we're not going to do that
inside of threats, right?
And so you can look at those.
Now, when you look at
these risk responses,
this is the way you're going
to address the primary risk.
But even after you
address the primary risk,
there is some residual risk left over
and that should also
receive a risk response too.
So if I was going back to my example
of the workstation being
installed on the network,
we're going to do
vulnerability management on it.
That should catch all
known vulnerabilities.
That mitigates down our risk to a low
because there are still
zero days out there
that vulnerability
management will not find.
Now what are you going to
do about those zero days?
Most people have learned to accept those
or they transfer it by buying some sort
of hacker or cyber insurance.
Some people will avoid it
by unplugging the device
from the network, right?
There's all sorts of responses you can do
but remember, there is residual risk
and you have to deal with that too.
And you're never going to
get your risk down to zero.
So you're going to have to, at some point,
either avoid it, transfer it,
reduce it, share it, accept it,
something from that threats column
or from the opportunities column,
depending on if it's a
negative or a positive risk.
Now, in PRINCE2 for the risk theme,
there are a couple of
things you just have to do.
The first is you have to define
your risk management approach
by describing your risk
management procedures to be used.
And this is done in your risk
management approach document.
You're also going to
maintain a risk register
to record and manage your risk.
You're then going to have to identify,
assess, manage and review your
risks throughout the project
because they change over time.
There is schedule slip risks.
There is over budget risk.
And the closer you get to
the end of the project,
the less likely that's going to happen.
Earlier in the project,
it's more likely to happen
because there's so many more variables.
You're also going to
need to define your roles
and responsibilities for risk management.
Going back to that principle,
and again, we want to use lessons learned
to help inform our risk decisions.
If you've only built one house,
it's a pretty risky process.
But if you built 100 of
that same floor plan,
that same house, it becomes less risky
because you have experience
and you know what you're doing.
This all is going to
factor into your risk,
into your risk budget
and into your risk tolerance
for a given project.