- Focus on Products
The Next principle of
PRINCE2 is Focus On Products,
and this asks the question
Are we delivering the required quality
that we've been tasked with?
Well, when we look at this,
we want to make sure that we
are successfully delivering
the products that lead to the benefits
of the products being realized.
So, if I want to deliver an
app, the app needs to work
to the approved quality of the end user.
Or if I'm going to build a house,
I want to make sure the homeowner
is happy with that house.
If I'm building a car, the
car has to do the things
that we outlined and the
benefits we said it was going to.
This is the idea of Focus On Products,
so PRINCE2 is all about
focusing on the end product
and the processes to get you there.
Now, when we look at that,
this is all about successful delivery.
The successful delivery of products
means that the stakeholder's
expectations are met.
Now, who are those stakeholders?
That was the end user, the supplier,
and the executive, right?
If those stakeholders are
having their expectations met,
you hit the bullseye.
We also want to meet
the agreed upon quality,
so if we said we were going to
build a network with 99% uptime,
and you finish building it after a year
and it's only getting 95% uptime,
did you get what we agreed upon?
Well, no, so you failed.
You didn't successfully
deliver the product.
But if you got it to
99.2, did you meet it?
Yes, you exceeded my
99% and that was great.
Also, we want to look at
Is this product fit for purpose?
Does it do what you
said it was going to do?
If you told me you were going
to build an electric car
that got 100 miles to a
charge and you built this car
and you could only get 75
miles, did it meet the purpose?
Was it fit for purpose?
Well, no, because I needed something
that did 100 miles, right?
So you have to make sure
you focus on the end result.
Even if you made me that electric car
and it was half the cost that
you told me it would cost,
I'm still not happy 'cause it didn't do
what I wanted it to do.
When we look at this, it's all
about Product-based Planning.
Other management methods like PMP
focus on an activity-based
planning, or how to to do things.
In PRINCE2, we're focusing on what to do.
We want to identify what
products need to be created,
and this becomes our checklist.
This is going to reduce
any kind of scope crypt from happening,
it's going to reduce the
likelihood that the user acceptance
doesn't happen and is disputed,
and it's also going to
reduce the likelihood
of users being dissatisfied,
because if the user says,
I want something that
does X and you deliver X,
they're happy, right?
That's the idea here.
It's all about Product-based Planning
and getting what you need done.
Now, how do you know
what the customer wants?
How do you agree to that?
Well, you use product descriptions.
This is going to delineate
exactly what the project will deliver.
Think about it like a blueprint.
It's going to contain the
purpose, the composition,
the specifications, the quality criteria,
the tolerance levels and
the acceptance criteria,
and this is all the things
we're going to agree on
before the project starts.
It's going to help the
project team to estimate
the amount of resources they
need, the time, the cost,
and what activities need to be done
in order to get the product
to its final delivery
and being accepted by the end customer.
So if I'm looking at a house example,
you'll look with the architect
about your blueprints,
and you'll say I want
the light switches here,
I want this type of air conditioning,
I want this type of tile.
You put all that detail into the plan
as a product description.
When you both sign off on it
and he delivers the house
and it has green carpet
and you signed off that
you wanted green carpet,
you can't complain
because you got what you asked for, right?
But if you put red carpet in
and the description said green carpet,
you can complain, right?
So that's the idea here
with product descriptions.
It's making sure that
everyone's on the same page
before we go and dig into this project
and start spending lots of time
and lots of resources on it.