- Manage by exception.
The manage by exception principle asks
one fundamental question:
how can we manage this
project more efficiently?
Well, one of the ways that we do that is
by using manage by exception,
and that is going to allow
only significant deviations
from a budget or an approved plan
to be brought to the
attention of management.
That's right, senior
management doesn't want to know
the day-to-day progress of the project.
Instead, they leave that
to the project manager
and the way they do this is
through using tolerances.
So because projects are so fluid,
they know that change is going to happen.
I'm going to budget $10,000 for this stage
but it may cost 9,000; it may cost 11,000
because changes happen.
How are we going to deal with that change?
Do I need to go back to the project board
every time there's going to be an issue?
Well no, instead by
using manage by exception
each project is going to
have tolerances built into it
for each project objective,
and delegated authorities
down to the project manager
for them to deal with it.
So in the case of this stage, say a cost
which is one of those project objectives,
if we have cost and we
say the cost is up to
$10,000 for this stage, and
you have a 10% tolerance,
that means you can spend
between 10 and $11,000.
If I forecast that this project
is going to cost $12,000
well now I need to go
talk to the project board
because I'm outside the
tolerance they gave me.
This allows project managers
to handle more of the issues
without having to involve senior managers
or the project board, and it
eliminates a ton of meetings
which makes us more efficient.
So, how do we do that?
Well as a project manager
I am going to submit
a highlight report, and the
highlight report is used
to keep the project board informed about
the progress of the project.
If a tolerance for the stage
is forecast to be exceeded
then I have to create an exception report
and send that to the project board.
So in the example of this stage and cost,
we said this stage is
allowed to cost $10,000
plus 10% tolerance.
So if I now forecast that
it's going to cost me 15,000
that's a 50% higher than I was allotted.
I need to put that into
an exception report,
tell the project board, and
ask either for more money
or some sort of a change.
That change may be to
relax some requirements
so that I can spend less money.
Or it may be to give me more money
so I can meet the requirements they want.
Everything is going to be a balancing act
between time and quality and cost,
and we'll talk more about
that as we go forward.
But for right now, I just
want you to understand
the concept of these tolerances.
For each of the objectives
we have a tolerance set,
and that may be something
that's don't go above
this amount of money, or don't go below
this amount of performance, right?
And we'll talk about
that as we go through.
The project objectives
we're talking about here
is time, and cost, and quality, and scope,
and benefits, and risk.
Each of these have to be balanced
and they're all set in the
initial initiation stage
for that program initiation documentation.
When I look at that PID it's going to say
this project must be completed in X time,
let's say six months.
If I think that I'm not
going to meet the six months,
I'm going to raise that as an exception.
Now with a highlight report,
I also can tell them good things.
I thought it was going to
cost me $10,000 for this stage
but I was able to do it for 5,000
and I saved you some money.
Quality, we need to have a
99% uptime on this network.
Well, am I meeting that or am I not?
What's my tolerance?
Same thing with scope, benefits, and risk.
All of these are things
that are those levers
that the project board uses
to control the project for us.
Now tolerances can be
set three different ways
and they get started by the
program or corporate management
when they approve the project plan.
They say for the project
level, the overall,
there's a certain amount of tolerance.
Let's say that they say
the project level tolerance
is 10% of cost.
This is going to be a
million dollar project
and I will allow a 10% variation.
Now the stage is going to be recommended
by the project manager and
approved by the project board.
Now if I was on the project board
and I knew I had a 10% tolerance,
that means I'm probably going
to give the project manager
something like a five or a 6% tolerance
so I have room to control if
he starts going out of bounds.
Then the project manager
can actually set tolerances
for his teams below him
in the work packages.
These are approved by the project manager
and usually if he has
a five or 6% tolerance
he might only give his
teams a one or 2% tolerance
because again, every time
a tolerance is exceeded
the next layer up is going to
have to deal with that change.
So if the team exceeds a tolerance
on the work package
level, the project manager
can still fix it before it flashes up
and goes all the way
up to the project level
which then has to go all the way up to
corporate and program management.
So you can see how
these things nestle down
and we try to keep them down
at the lowest level possible
so we can keep progress moving forward.
So what are some benefits
of management by exception?
Well, it allows senior
management to focus on strategy
without getting overburdened
by daily decisions
of the project.
So for example here, you see a Navy ship,
it's out and about doing its mission.
The Chief of Naval
Operations who's sitting
in Washington D.C. is
not telling that ship
to turn left or to turn right.
Instead, he gives them a plan and he says,
"I want you to go from
California to Australia."
Then it's up to the ship to figure out
how they're going to get
from one place to the other
because they've delegated that down.
So that's up to them to figure that out.
Now on the ship there's a
captain who is in charge
and he doesn't want to
be up 24 hours a day
seven days a week, so he delegates down
some of that as well.
So he might say, "Okay, for the next day
"I want to get from point A to point B.
"Navigator, figure that out."
Then the navigator can figure that out
and he'll give it to the watch teams
and he'll say, "Okay, you
go from point A to here
"and then the next team
will take it from there
"to the next point,"
and you get the idea, right?
They keep breaking it down
into smaller and smaller chunks
and as long as they stay
within the tolerances
nobody has to report back to
the guy in Washington D.C.
to say we got there or we didn't.
That's all they have to report,
we did it, or we didn't,
or we went too far out of bounds.
That's the idea here.
It becomes an efficient use
of senior management's time.
There are no regular progress meetings
because we have these highlight reports
and these exception reports,
and there's no in-between
meetings that are happening
between the project manager
and the project board.
Now that is according to PRINCE2
but your organization may be different.
I've worked in a lot of organizations
where they love their
weekly progress meetings.
So everybody sits around
a table for an hour
on a Monday morning and says,
"Here's what we're doing this week,"
and then on Friday they
all come back and say,
"Here's what we finished this week,"
and it's really a waste of time.
But if they use that
management by exception,
those meetings can be eliminated
so it really is crucial.
So how do you really do
management by exception well?
Provide good tolerances for your people
and empower them to make decisions
to stay within those tolerances.
If you can do that, you will
have a very successful project.
(quick electronic music)