- Tailor to suit the project environment.
So the last principle that we have is
tailoring to suit the project environment.
And this asks the question how can PRINCE2
be adapted based on the size, scope
or complexity of the project to
meet the needs that we have.
Do we have to have a one
size fits all solution?
Well, of course not.
And that's the great thing about PRINCE2
is that it's highly adaptable,
specifically to each and every project.
The projects are going to occur
in many different contexts.
There's going to be cultural context,
geographical context, complexity,
and scale, and risk context.
Every project is a little bit different,
but PRINCE2 can work with them all
if you want to tailor it.
So, when we look at it,
how do you adapt PRINCE2?
Well, tailoring and adapting
PRINCE2 is pretty easy.
You can add things to it and
make it fit your organization.
So I mentioned in the manage
by exception principle,
that some people just do
away with the board meetings
because they're not required under PRINCE2
because you have this highlight
report that replaces them.
But many organizations still want to have
those regular progress meetings
and that's okay because in PRINCE2
that would be considered
an adaption or tailoring
of PRINCE2 to your
organizational standards.
There is nothing wrong with adding those
meetings if you want to.
But if you wanted to
take away the highlight
reports all-together, that really
wouldn't be much like PRINCE2 and so
adding is okay, but
taking away often is not.
Now, what do I do if
my organization tailors
PRINCE2 and we add those meetings,
or we add additional steps?
Well, you should document
any of those changes
inside the PID, or the Project
Initiation Documentation.
Remember, that's the document that we
set up before we started the project,
in the initiation stage.
This is going to provide an audit trail,
and evidence, that you're
compliant with PRINCE2
and that your organization is changing
things based on your standards.
This allows any time you
have an external audit
to come in, to go 'yep'
they're doing PRINCE2
even though they've added
this, this, this, and this.
Right? So this is an idea
that you want to make sure
you're documenting things
that are being changed.
Now, what if your project
is really, really small?
Can I drop things that are PRINCE2?
Well, no, you should still go through
every theme and every
process inside of PRINCE2
because otherwise you might
become an organization
that is doing PRINCE2 in name only and
you're losing a lot of
the benefits of PRINCE2.
So, what can you do when
your project is really small?
Well, you can speed up
or scale down processes
because each theme and process
needs to be considered,
but it might be considered for
just a short period of time.
Now, what does this really look like?
Well, if you've ever made a pizza,
you can make a personal pizza,
you can make a full size pizza,
or you can make a three foot wide pizza,
it just matters on whether you scale up
or scale down your ingredients.
PRINCE2 is much the same, you're still
going to need all of the ingredients.
You still need all the
themes and all the processes,
but you can go through
them very quickly if needed
and that will allow you to get through it
in a small environment
much quicker than having
to bring together the
full scale of PRINCE2.
And again, that's where
that adaption comes in.
Now, can you change what things
are called inside of PRINCE2?
Well, certainly. And the good news is
you're not breaking rules by doing it.
Terminology can be
difficult and confusing and
people call things all
sorts of different things.
The important thing is
that we're all using
common terminology and
you can use the PRINCE2
term and that will give you a common
terminology or your organization can
change those terms as
long as the organization
consistently uses the same wording.
So, for example, many organizations don't
use the PRINCE2 term of
Project Product Description.
Instead, they call it
a Requirements Document
and that's perfectly fine.
My organization, we call it
our Requirements Document.
Everybody knows that's what it is,
it still meets all the requirement for
a Project Product Description,
we just call it a Requirements Document.
And that's perfectly acceptable.
It also allows us to
keep our terms consistent
throughout, so I don't really care
what you call the thing, as long
as you call it the same thing every time.
Because that way everyone on the
team knows what you're talking about.
And it's really helpful to
create a glossary of terms.
So if you're not going to use the
standard PRINCE2 terminology,
you should have your own mini-dictionary,
essentially, that says we call
it a Requirements Document and that
equates to Project Product Description.
And so if you can have that cross
reference documentation, go ahead
and put that into an annex into your PID,
that way everyone knows what everything
is being called and you're going to
stay within the PRINCE2 framework.
Now, each piece of
PRINCE2 is very important
and no part of the
methodology should be ignored.
We already talked about the fact that
you need to go through all seven themes.
The business case, the organization,
the quality, the plans, the risk,
the change, the progress and
all seven of the processes.
But you may do them in shorter
time or scale them down.
Adapting PRINCE2 is a good thing,
in fact it's a great thing because
it focuses on the decisions being made
by the managers and not necessarily
on documents and templates and meetings.
That is the pure power of PRINCE2.
And why it is such a
great methodology to use
for your project management.
Now, can I add more
themes during tailoring?
Certainly. PRINCE2 only gives you
those seven themes we just talked about,
but you can always add more.
So maybe you need a human resource theme,
or a communications theme,
or a legal theme, or a financial,
or a health and safety, or something
else that really applies
only to your business.
That's okay, your
organization can add these in,
but please don't take away the seven
core themes because that's going to hurt
your project and put you more at risk.