- Directing A Project.
Now, I know you were excited
to get in to Initiating A Project
because we've just left
Starting Up A Project,
but first, we have to direct the project,
and this is going to happen
across multiple phases
in the project.
We'll talk about Directing A Project,
we're talking about how we're
going to enable our Project Board
to be accountable for
the project's success
by making those key
decisions and exercising
the overall control, while
delegating our day-to-day
management of the project
down to the project manager.
Remember, we want to manage by exception.
We want to push down those
authorities when we can
to free up the executive's time.
Now, when we look at this
on the Process Timeline,
you can see where Directing a Project is.
It's going to cover this Directing layer,
and it's going to go across
the Initiation Stage,
the Subsequent Stages,
and the Final Stage,
and so, it's really, really important,
because it really is the bridge
across our Process Timeline.
So when we deal with Directing A Process,
we have a couple of objectives.
First, we need to provide authority
to initiate the project,
to get it started,
to deliver the project's products,
and to close the project.
Anytime we want to move
from one stage to another,
we are going to be utilizing
Directing A Project's process.
This is going to provide
management the direction
and control throughout the
project's entire lifecycle,
and it's going to ensure that
the project remains viable,
because before we leave one
stage and go to the next,
we're going to get that go/no-go decision
through Directing A Project.
Next, we want to make sure
it provides the corporate,
the program management, or the customer,
an interface within the project,
and that is through this Project Board
that does Directing A Project,
and it's going to manage and
review the post-project benefits
to make sure that the product
that the project makes
does meet the requirements
that were set out
and agreed upon all the
back in the original
Starting Up A Project phase
and the Initializing A Project,
which we'll talk about in the next lesson.
Now, what is going to trigger
Directing A Project process?
Well, this process is
going to be initiated
and begin, once the Starting
Up A Project process
is completed.
Once that mandate has been received,
and the request to initiate is received,
we are going to go ahead and
start directing this project,
because we've now identified
who is those key roles
on the Project Board.
That Project Board is now
responsible for ensuring
that a business justification exists,
and continues to exist
through every other stage
of the project.
They're going to utilize
manage by exception
to direct the progress, and
allow the project manager
to do their job on a day-to-day basis
and take care of the minor issues.
Anytime it's something that has to come up
through an exception, it goes back up here
to Directing A Project
process for a decision.
When I think of Directing
A Project process,
I think about decision making,
specifically at the Project Board,
and so there are five key activities
that the Project Board is
going to be concerned with.
They need to authorize the
initiation of the project
and ensure that the
investment is worthwhile.
They need to authorize the project itself.
Their going to approve the
Project Initiation Document,
which is going to be created
in the Initialization Stage,
which we're going to talk about next,
and if they think this
project has a firm foundation.
That we know, the scope, the
cost, the time, the risk,
the benefits, who's responsible for what,
and how progress will be monitored.
All of that has to be shown
in the Progress Initiation Document,
so that they can authorize the project.
The third thing they
do is authorize a stage
or an exception plan.
Remember, they're going to
create the overall project plan
and approve it, and then they're
going to authorize stage plans
or exception plans to go forward,
when there's an issue
or when there's a plan
created by the project manager.
They're going to review the
performance of the current stage
and approve the next stage,
before they move forward.
They're also going to
approve product descriptions
as part of that plan, so they know
what they're going to get out of it,
and what the end product of
that stage is going to be,
and they're going to
review the lessons report
and decide who should receive them.
Should it stay within this project,
or should they share
it with other projects?
That is something that the
Project Board is going to handle.
Fourth, they're going to
give ad-hoc direction,
and that means they're going to
review the highlight reports,
the issue, and the exception reports.
They're going to make
decisions about these issues,
the risks, and the changes,
and they're going to give
advice to that project manager,
and finally, they're going
to communicate that up
and across to the different stakeholders.
The fifth and final activity
they're going to do,
is authorizing the closure of the project,
and that means they're
going to approve and review
the end project report that is created
by the project manager, as
well as their lessons report.
Once they take all that information,
they can then go in to and
approve the project closure,
and we'll talk about that and what happens
in Closing A Project.